<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3CR3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>
<sect1 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" id="ch-scripts-bootscripts" xreflabel="Bootscripts">
<title>Installing LFS-Bootscripts-&bootscripts-version;</title>
<?dbhtml filename="bootscripts.html"?>

<para>The LFS-Bootscripts package contains a set of bootscripts.</para>

<screen>&buildtime; 0.1 SBU
&diskspace; 0.3 MB</screen>

<literallayout>Official download location for LFS-Bootscripts (&bootscripts-version;):
<ulink url="&http-down;"/></literallayout>

<para>For its installation LFS-Bootscripts depends on: Bash, Coreutils.</para>



<sect2>
<title>Installation of LFS-Bootscripts</title>

<para>Install the boot scripts simply by copying them to their
destination:</para>

<screen><userinput>cp -a rc.d sysconfig /etc</userinput></screen>

<para>Make sure <emphasis>root</emphasis> is owner of the scripts:</para>

<screen><userinput>chown -R root:root /etc/rc.d /etc/sysconfig</userinput></screen>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="contents-bootscripts"><title>Contents of LFS-bootscripts</title>

<para><emphasis>Installed scripts</emphasis>: checkfs, cleanfs, functions,
halt, ifdown, ifup, loadkeys, localnet, mountfs, mountproc, network, rc,
reboot, sendsignals, setclock, swap, sysklogd and template</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para>The <command>checkfs</command> script checks the file systems just
before they are mounted (with the exception of journal and network based
file systems).</para>

<para>The <command>cleanfs</command> script removes files that shouldn't be
preserved between reboots, such as those in <filename>/var/run/</filename> and
<filename>/var/lock/</filename>. It re-creates <filename>/var/run/utmp</filename>
and removes the possibly present <filename>/etc/nologin</filename>,
<filename>/fastboot</filename> and <filename>/forcefsck</filename> files.</para>

<para>The <command>functions</command> script contains functions shared among
different scripts, such as error and status checking.</para>

<para>The <command>halt</command> script halts the system.</para>

<para>The <command>ifdown</command> and <command>ifup</command> scripts assist
the network script with network devices.</para>

<para>The <command>loadkeys</command> script loads the keymap table you
specified as proper for your keyboard layout.</para>

<para>The <command>localnet</command> script sets up the system's hostname and
local loopback device.</para>

<para>The <command>mountfs</command> script mounts all file systems that
aren't marked <emphasis>noauto</emphasis> or aren't network based.</para>

<para>The <command>mountproc</command> script is used to mount the proc
file system.</para>

<para>The <command>network</command> script sets up network interfaces, such
as network cards, and sets up the default gateway where applicable.</para>

<para>The <command>rc</command> script is the master runlevel control script.
It is responsible for running all the other scripts one-by-one in a specific
sequence.</para>

<para>The <command>reboot</command> script reboots the system.</para>

<para>The <command>sendsignals</command> script makes sure every process is
terminated before the system reboots or halts.</para>

<para>The <command>setclock</command> script resets the kernel clock to
localtime in case the hardware clock isn't set to GMT time.</para>

<para>The <command>swap</command> script enables and disables swap files and
partitions.</para>

<para>The <command>sysklogd</command> script starts and stops the system and
kernel log daemons.</para>

<para>The <command>template</command> script is a template you can use to
create your own bootscripts for your other daemons.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>
