<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="ch05-filingbug">
  <title>Enter a new bug</title>
  <?dbhtml filename="enternewbug.html"?>

  <para>You found a bug, or somebody else found a bug and you decided to add
    it to Trac.  Or, you want to log a request for a feature that somebody has
    asked for, or a task of some other type.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para>Go to <ulink url="http://wiki.linuxfromscratch.org/lfs/newticket"/>
    </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Select the ticket type (defect for bugs, or enhancement,
    or task). </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>The <emphasis>Short summary</emphasis> and <emphasis>
    Full Description</emphasis> are mandatory.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Select the <emphasis>Priority</emphasis>. Use your
    own judgement on how important fixing this bug is. If you're not sure just
    leave the default. Priorities are periodically re-evaluated and changed
    anyway.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Select the <emphasis>Component</emphasis> - the only
    options are Book or Bootscripts.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Select the <emphasis>Severity</emphasis> as appropriate,
    anything from trivial to critical or blocker.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>If you don't want to assign yourself to it right away, leave
    the <emphasis>Assign To</emphasis> field blank. It'll be assigned to
    <email>lfs-book@linuxfromscratch.org</email> then, until a real editor
    changes that to himself.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>If you wish, select a <emphasis>Milestone</emphasis>, either
    the next version, or future.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Select the proper <emphasis>Version</emphasis>. You most
    always will choose the <emphasis>SVN</emphasis> version. It doesn't make
    sense to report a bug against an old version if it's no longer in Subversion. If it
    is, then SVN is newer than a previously released stable book version.  The
    versions are basically there only for people who don't edit the book and who
    want to report a bug against the book version they have.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Fill in the <emphasis>Keywords</emphasis> and <emphasis>Cc:
    </emphasis> fields if you wish.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Particularly if you are using any formatting in the Full 
    description field, you may wish to click on the <emphasis>Preview</emphasis>
   button.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>As the last step, click on the <emphasis>Submit ticket</emphasis>
    button to commit your changes to the database. A log of this will be sent to
    the <email>lfs-book@linuxfromscratch.org</email> mailinglist.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

