<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="ch05-filingbug">
  <title>Enter a new bug</title>
  <?dbhtml filename="enternewbug.html"?>

  <para>You found a bug, or somebody else found a bug and you decided to add
    it to Bugzilla.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para>Go to <ulink url="http://bugs.linuxfromscratch.org/enter_bug.cgi"/>
    </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Select the proper <emphasis>Version</emphasis>. You most
    always will choose the <emphasis>SVN</emphasis> version. It doesn't make
    sense to report a bug against an old version if it's no longer in Subversion. If it
    is, then SVN is newer than a previously released stable book version.  The
    versions are basically there only for people who don't edit the book and who
    want to report a bug against the book version they have.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Don't worry about <emphasis>Component, Platform, OS and
    Severity</emphasis> Those aren't used at the moment.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Select the <emphasis>Resolution Priority</emphasis>. Use your
    own judgement on how important fixing this bug is. If you're not sure just
    leave the default. Priorities are periodically re-evaluated and changed
    anyway (what may be P5 a month ago may be changed to a P1 now because it's
    finally time to fix it).</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Select the <emphasis>Initial state</emphasis>. Only select
    <emphasis>UNCONFIRMED</emphasis> if you haven't checked the matter out yet
    and are only suspecting a bug. Otherwise, leave it as
    <emphasis>NEW</emphasis></para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>If you don't want to assign yourself to it right away, leave
    the <emphasis>Assigned To</emphasis> field blank. It'll be assigned to
    <emphasis>lfs-book@linuxfromscratch.org</emphasis> then, until a real editor
    changes that to himself.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Fill in the other fields as appropriate,
    <emphasis>Summary</emphasis> and <emphasis>Description</emphasis> are
    mandatory.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>As the last step, click on the <emphasis>Commit</emphasis>
    button to commit your changes to the database. A log of this will be sent to
    the lfs-book mailinglist.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

