<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3CR2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3CR2/docbookx.dtd">
<appendix id="appendixa" xreflabel="Appendix A">
<?dbhtml dir="appendixa"?>
<title>Package descriptions and dependencies</title>
<?dbhtml filename="appendixa.html"?>

<sect1 id="aa-intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>

<para>In this appendix the following aspects of every package
installed in this book are described:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>the official download location for the 
package,</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>what the package contains,</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>what each program from the package does,</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>what the package needs to be compiled.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>Most information about these packages (especially the descriptions of
them) come from the man pages of those packages. We do not include
the entire man page, but just some key elements to make it possible to
understand what a program does. To get information on all details of a program, 
please refer to its man page or info page.</para>

<para>Certain packages are documented in more depth
than others, because we just happen to know more about certain
packages than about others. If you think anything should be added to the
following descriptions, please don't hesitate to email the mailing
lists. We intend that the list should contain an in-depth description 
of every package installed, but we can't do it without help.</para>

<para>Please note that currently only what a package does is described and not
why it needs to be installed. This may be added later.</para>

<para>Also listed are all of the installation dependencies for all the
packages that are installed in this book. The listings will include
which programs from which packages are needed to successfully compile
the package to be installed.</para>

<para>These are not running dependencies, meaning they don't tell you
what programs are needed to use that package's programs, just the ones
needed to compile it.</para>

<para>The dependency list can be, from time to time, outdated in regards
to the currently used package version. Checking dependencies takes quite a
bit of work, so they may lag behind a bit on the package update. But
often with minor package updates, the installation dependencies hardly
change, so they'll be current in most cases. When we upgrade to a major
new release, we'll make sure the dependencies are checked too.</para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-autoconf" xreflabel="Autoconf">
<title>Autoconf</title>
<?dbhtml filename="autoconf.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-autoconf"/>.</para>

<sect2>

<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Autoconf (2.59): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/autoconf/"/></literallayout>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Autoconf</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &autoconf-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Autoconf produces shell scripts which automatically configure source
code.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: autoconf, autoheader, autom4te,
autoreconf, autoscan, autoupdate and ifnames</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>autoconf</command> is a tool for producing shell scripts
that automatically configure software source code packages to adapt to many
kinds of Unix-like systems. The configuration scripts it produces are
independent -- running them does not require the autoconf program.</para>

<para><command>autoheader</command> is a tool for creating template files
of C #define statements for configure to use.</para>

<para><command>autom4te</command> is a wrapper for the M4 macro
processor.</para>

<para><command>autoreconf</command> comes in handy when there are a lot
of autoconf-generated configure scripts around. The program runs autoconf and
autoheader repeatedly (where appropriate) to remake the autoconf configure
scripts and configuration header templates in a given directory tree.</para>

<para><command>autoscan</command> can help to create a
<filename>configure.in</filename> file for a software package. It examines
the source files in a directory tree, searching them for common portability
problems and creates a <filename>configure.scan</filename> file that serves as
as a preliminary <filename>configure.in</filename> for the package.</para>

<para><command>autoupdate</command> modifies a 
<filename>configure.in</filename> file that still calls autoconf macros
by their old names to use the current macro names.</para>

<para><command>ifnames</command> can be helpful when writing a
<filename>configure.in</filename> for a software package. It prints the
identifiers that the package uses in C preprocessor conditionals. If a package
has already been set up to have some portability, this program can help to
determine what <userinput>configure</userinput> needs to check. It can fill
in some gaps in a <filename>configure.in</filename> file generated by
autoscan.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Autoconf Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &autoconf-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Autoconf depends on: Bash, Coreutils, Diffutils, Grep,
M4, Make, Perl, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-automake" xreflabel="Automake">
<title>Automake</title>
<?dbhtml filename="automake.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-automake"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Automake (1.8): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/automake/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Automake</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &automake-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Automake generates Makefile.in files, intended for use with Autoconf.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: acinstall, aclocal,
aclocal-1.8, automake, automake-1.8, compile, config.guess, config.sub,
depcomp, elisp-comp, install-sh, mdate-sh, missing, mkinstalldirs, py-compile,
symlink-tree, ylwrap</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>acinstall</command> is a script that installs
aclocal-style M4 files.</para>

<para><command>aclocal</command> generates <filename>aclocal.m4</filename>
files based on the contents of <filename>configure.in</filename> files.</para>

<para><command>automake</command> is a tool for automatically generating
<filename>Makefile.in</filename>'s from files called
<filename>Makefile.am</filename>. To create all the
<filename>Makefile.in</filename> files for a package, run this program in the
top level directory. By scanning the <filename>configure.in</filename>s it
automatically finds each appropriate <filename>Makefile.am</filename> and
generate the corresponding <filename>Makefile.in</filename>.</para>

<para><command>compile</command> is a wrapper for compilers.</para>

<para><command>config.guess</command> is a script that attempts to guess
the canonical triplet for the given build, host, or target architecture.</para>

<para><command>config.sub</command> is a configuration validation
subroutine script.</para>

<para><command>depcomp</command> is a script for compiling a program
so that not only the desired output is generated but also dependency
information.</para>

<para><command>elisp-comp</command> byte-compiles Emacs Lisp code.</para>

<para><command>install-sh</command> is a script that installs a program,
a script, or a datafile.</para>

<para><command>mdate-sh</command> is a script that prints the modification
time of a file or directory.</para>

<para><command>missing</command> is a script acting as a common stub for
missing GNU programs during an installation.</para>

<para><command>mkinstalldirs</command> is a script that creates a directory
tree.</para>

<para><command>py-compile</command> compiles a Python program.</para>

<para><command>symlink-tree</command> is a script to create a symlink tree of
a directory tree.</para>

<para><command>ylwrap</command> is a wrapper for lex and yacc.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Automake Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &automake-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Automake depends on: Autoconf, Bash, Coreutils,
Diffutils, Grep, M4, Make, Perl, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-bash" xreflabel="Bash">
<title>Bash</title>
<?dbhtml filename="bash.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-bash"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Bash (2.05b): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/bash/"/>

Bash Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/bash-2.05b-2.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Contents of Bash</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &bash-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>bash is the Bourne-Again SHell, which is a widely used command
interpreter on Unix systems. The bash program reads from standard
input (the keyboard). A user types something and the program will evaluate
what he has typed and do something with it, like running a
program.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: bash, sh (link to bash) and
bashbug</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>bash</command> is a widely-used command interpreter. It
performs all kinds of expansions and substitutions on a given command line
before executing it, thus making this interpreter a powerful tool.</para>

<para><command>bashbug</command> is a shell script to help the user
compose and mail bug reports concerning bash in a standard format.</para>

<para><command>sh</command> is a symlink to the bash program. When invoked
as sh, bash tries to mimic the startup behavior of historical versions of sh as
closely as possible, while conforming to the POSIX standard as well.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Bash Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &bash-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Bash depends on: Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils, Gawk,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Ncurses, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-binutils" xreflabel="Binutils">
<title>Binutils</title>
<?dbhtml filename="binutils.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-binutils"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Binutils (2.14): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/binutils/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Contents of Binutils</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &binutils-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Binutils is a collection of software development tools containing a
linker, assembler and other tools to work with object files and
archives.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: addr2line, ar, as, c++filt,
gprof, ld, nm, objcopy, objdump, ranlib, readelf, size, strings and
strip</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed libraries</emphasis>: libiberty.a, libbfd.[a,so] and
libopcodes.[a,so]</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>addr2line</command> translates program addresses to file
names and line numbers. Given an address and the name of an executable, it
uses the debugging information in the executable to figure out which source
file and line number are associated with the address.</para>

<para><command>ar</command> creates, modifies, and extracts from archives. An archive
is a single file holding a collection of other files in a structure that makes
it possible to retrieve the original individual files (called members of
the archive).</para>

<para><command>as</command> is an assembler. It assembles the output of
gcc into object files.</para>

<para><command>c++filt</command> is used by the linker to demangle C++ and
Java symbols, to keep overloaded functions from clashing.</para>

<para><command>gprof</command> displays call graph profile data.</para>

<para><command>ld</command> is a linker. It combines a number of object
and archive files into a single file, relocating their data and tying up symbol
references.</para>

<para><command>nm</command> lists the symbols occurring in a given object file.</para>

<para><command>objcopy</command> is used to translate one type of object
file into another.</para>

<para><command>objdump</command> displays information about the given
object file, with options controlling what particular information to display.
The information shown is mostly only useful to programmers who are working on
the compilation tools.</para>

<para><command>ranlib</command> generates an index of the contents of an
archive, and stores it in the archive. The index lists all the symbols defined
by archive members that are relocatable object files.</para>

<para><command>readelf</command> displays information about elf type binaries.</para>

<para><command>size</command> lists the section sizes -- and the grand
total -- for the given object files.</para>

<para><command>strings</command> outputs for each file given the sequences
of printable characters that are of at least the specified length (defaulting to 4)
For object files it prints by default only the strings from the initializing
and loading sections. For other types of files it scans the whole file.</para>

<para><command>strip</command> discards symbols from object files.</para>

<para><command>libiberty</command> contains routines used by various GNU
programs, including getopt, obstack, strerror, strtol and strtoul.</para>

<para><command>libbfd</command> is the Binary File Descriptor library.</para>

<para><command>libopcodes</command> is a library for dealing with opcodes.
It is used for building utilities like objdump. Opcodes are the "readable text"
versions of instructions for the processor.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Binutils Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &binutils-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Binutils depends on: Bash, Coreutils, Diffutils, GCC, Gettext,
Glibc, Grep, Make, Perl, Sed, Texinfo.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-bison" xreflabel="Bison">
<title>Bison</title>
<?dbhtml filename="bison.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-bison"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Bison (1.875): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/bison/"/>

Bison Attribute Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/bison-1.875-attribute.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Contents of Bison</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &bison-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Bison is a parser generator, a replacement for yacc. Bison
generates a program that analyzes the structure of a text file.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: bison and yacc</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed library</emphasis>: liby.a</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>bison</command> generates, from a series of rules, a program
for analyzing the structure of text files. Bison is a replacement for yacc
(Yet Another Compiler Compiler).</para>

<para><command>yacc</command> is a wrapper for bison, meant for programs
that still call yacc instead of bison. It calls bison with the -y option.</para>

<para><command>liby.a</command> is the Yacc library containing
implementations of Yacc-compatible yyerror and main functions. This library
is normally not very useful, but POSIX requires it.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Bison Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &bison-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Bison depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, M4, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-bzip2" xreflabel="Bzip2">
<title>Bzip2</title>
<?dbhtml filename="bzip2.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-bzip2"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Bzip2 (1.0.2): 
<ulink url="http://sources.redhat.com/bzip2/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Bzip2</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &bzip2-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Bzip2 is a block-sorting file compressor which generally achieves a
better compression than the traditional <userinput>gzip</userinput>
does.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: bunzip2 (link to bzip2), bzcat
(link to bzip2), bzcmp, bzdiff, bzegrep, bzfgrep, bzgrep, bzip2, bzip2recover,
bzless and bzmore</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed libraries</emphasis>: libbz2.a, libbz2.so (link to
libbz2.so.1.0), libbz2.so.1.0 (link to libbz2.so.1.0.2) and
libbz2.so.1.0.2</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>bunzip2</command> decompresses bzipped files.</para>

<para><command>bzcat</command> decompresses to standard output.</para>

<para><command>bzcmp</command> runs cmp on bzipped files.</para>

<para><command>bzdiff</command> runs diff on bzipped files.</para>

<para><command>bzgrep</command> and friends run grep on bzipped files.</para>

<para><command>bzip2</command> compresses files using the Burrows-Wheeler
block sorting text compression algorithm with Huffman coding. The compression
rate is generally considerably better than that achieved by more conventional
compressors using LZ77/LZ78, like <userinput>gzip</userinput>.</para>

<para><command>bzip2recover</command> tries to recover data from damaged
bzip2 files.</para>

<para><command>bzless</command> runs less on bzipped files.</para>

<para><command>bzmore</command> runs more on bzipped files.</para>

<para><command>libbz2*</command> is the library implementing lossless,
block-sorting data compression, using the Burrows-Wheeler algorithm.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Bzip2 Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &bzip2-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Bzip2 depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Glibc, Make.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-coreutils" xreflabel="Coreutils">
<title>Coreutils</title>
<?dbhtml filename="coreutils.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-coreutils"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Coreutils (5.0):
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/coreutils/"/>

Coreutils Hostname Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/coreutils-5.0-hostname-2.patch"/>

Coreutils Uname Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/coreutils-5.0-uname.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Coreutils</title>

<para>The Coreutils package contains a whole series of basic shell utilities.</para>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &coreutils-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: basename, cat, chgrp, chmod,
chown, chroot, cksum, comm, cp, csplit, cut, date, dd, df, dir, dircolors,
dirname, du, echo, env, expand, expr, factor, false, fmt, fold, groups, head,
hostid, hostname, id, install, join, link, ln, logname, ls, md5sum,
mkdir, mkfifo, mknod, mv, nice, nl, nohup, od, paste, pathchk, pinky, pr,
printenv, printf, ptx, pwd, readlink, rm, rmdir, seq, sha1sum, shred, sleep,
sort, split, stat, stty, su, sum, sync, tac, tail, tee, test, touch, tr, true,
tsort, tty, uname, unexpand, uniq, unlink, uptime, users, vdir, wc, who,
whoami and yes</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>basename</command> strips any path and a given suffix from
the given file name.</para>

<para><command>cat</command> concatenates files to standard output.</para>

<para><command>chgrp</command> changes the group ownership of each given
file to the given group. The group can be either given a a name or a numeric
ID.</para>

<para><command>chmod</command> changes the permissions of each given file
to the given mode. The mode can be either a symbolic representation of the
changes to make, or an octal number representing the new permissions.</para>

<para><command>chown</command> changes the user and/or group ownership of
each given file to the given user:group pair.</para>

<para><command>chroot</command> runs a given command with the specified
directory as the <filename>/</filename> directory. The given command can be an
interactive shell. On most systems only <emphasis>root</emphasis> can do
this.</para>

<para><command>cksum</command> prints the CRC checksum and the byte
counts of each specified file.</para>

<para><command>comm</command> compares two sorted files, outputting in
three columns the lines that are unique, and the lines that are common.</para>

<para><command>cp</command> copies files.</para>

<para><command>csplit</command> splits a given file into several new files,
separating them according to given patterns or line numbers, and outputting
the byte count of each new file.</para>

<para><command>cut</command> prints parts of lines, selecting the parts
according to given fields or positions.</para>

<para><command>date</command> displays the current time in the given
format, or sets the system date.</para>

<para><command>dd</command> copies a file using the given blocksize and
count, while optionally performing conversions on it.</para>

<para><command>df</command> reports the amount of disk space available
(and used) on all mounted filesystems, or only on the filesystems holding the
given files.</para>

<para><command>dir</command> is the same as ls.</para>

<para><command>dircolors</command> outputs commands to set the LS_COLOR
environment variable, to change the color scheme used by ls.</para>

<para><command>dirname</command> strips the non-directory suffix from
a given file name.</para>

<para><command>du</command> reports the amount of disk space used by the
current directory, or by each of the given directories including all their
subdirectories, or by each of the given files.</para>

<para><command>echo</command> displays the given strings.</para>

<para><command>env</command> runs a command in a modified environment.</para>

<para><command>expand</command> converts tabs to spaces.</para>

<para><command>expr</command> evaluates expressions.</para>

<para><command>factor</command> prints the prime factors of all specified
integer numbers.</para>

<para><command>false</command> does nothing, unsuccessfully. It always
exits with a status code indicating failure.</para>

<para><command>fmt</command> reformats the paragraphs in the given files.</para>

<para><command>fold</command> wraps the lines in the given files.</para>

<para><command>groups</command> reports a user's group memberships.</para>

<para><command>head</command> prints the first ten lines (or the given
number of lines) of each given file.</para>

<para><command>hostid</command> reports the numeric identifier
(in hexadecimal) of the host.</para>

<para><command>hostname</command> reports or sets the name of the
host.</para>

<para><command>id</command> reports the effective user ID, group ID, and
group memberships of the current user, or of a given user.</para>

<para><command>install</command> copies files while setting their
permission modes and, if possible, their owner and group.</para>

<para><command>join</command> joins from two files the lines that have
identical join fields.</para>

<para><command>link</command> creates a hard link with the given name
to the given file.</para>

<para><command>ln</command> makes hard links or soft links between files.</para>

<para><command>logname</command> reports the current user's login name.</para>

<para><command>ls</command> lists the contents of each given directory.
By default it orders the files and subdirectories alphabetically.</para>

<para><command>md5sum</command> reports or checks MD5 checksums.</para>

<para><command>mkdir</command> creates directories with the given names.</para>

<para><command>mkfifo</command> creates FIFOs with the given names.</para>

<para><command>mknod</command> creates device nodes with the given names.
A device node is a character special file, or a block special file, or a FIFO.</para>

<para><command>mv</command> moves or renames files or directories.</para>

<para><command>nice</command> runs a program with modified scheduling priority.</para>

<para><command>nl</command> numbers the lines from the given files.</para>

<para><command>nohup</command> runs a command immune to hangups, with
output redirected to a log file.</para>

<para><command>od</command> dumps files in octal and other formats.</para>

<para><command>paste</command> merges the given files, joining
sequentially corresponding lines side by side, separated by TABs.</para>

<para><command>pathchk</command> checks whether file names are valid
or portable.</para>

<para><command>pinky</command> is a lightweight finger. It reports
some information about the given users.</para>

<para><command>pr</command> paginates and columnates files for printing.</para>

<para><command>printenv</command> prints the environment.</para>

<para><command>printf</command> prints the given arguments according to the
given format -- much like the C printf function.</para>

<para><command>ptx</command> produces from the contents of the given files
a permuted index, with each keyword in its context.</para>

<para><command>pwd</command> reports the name of the current directory.</para>

<para><command>readlink</command> reports the value of the given symbolic
link.</para>

<para><command>rm</command> removes files or directories.</para>

<para><command>rmdir</command> removes directories, if they are empty.</para>

<para><command>seq</command> prints a sequence of numbers, within a given
range and with a given increment.</para>

<para><command>sha1sum</command> prints or checks 160-bit SHA1
checksums.</para>

<para><command>shred</command> overwrites the given files repeatedly with
strange patterns, to make it real hard to recover the data.</para>

<para><command>sleep</command> pauses for the given amount of time.</para>

<para><command>sort</command> sorts the lines from the given files.</para>

<para><command>split</command> splits the given file into pieces, by size
or by number of lines.</para>

<para><command>stty</command> sets or reports terminal line settings.</para>

<para><command>su</command> runs a shell with substitute user and group IDs.</para>

<para><command>sum</command> prints checksum and block counts for each
given file.</para>

<para><command>sync</command> flushes filesystem buffers. It forces
changed blocks to disk and updates the super block.</para>

<para><command>tac</command> concatenates the given files in reverse.</para>

<para><command>tail</command> prints the last ten lines (or the given
number of lines) of each given file.</para>

<para><command>tee</command> reads from standard input while writing both
to standard output and to the given files.</para>

<para><command>test</command> compares values and checks file types.</para>

<para><command>touch</command> changes file timestamps, setting the access
and modification times of the given files to the current time. Files that do
not exist are created with zero length.</para>

<para><command>tr</command> translates, squeezes, and deletes the given
characters from standard input.</para>

<para><command>true</command> does nothing, successfully. It always exits
with a status code indicating success.</para>

<para><command>tsort</command> performs a topological sort. It writes a
totally ordered list according to the partial ordering in a given file.</para>

<para><command>tty</command> reports the file name of the terminal
connected to standard input.</para>

<para><command>uname</command> reports system information.</para>

<para><command>unexpand</command> converts spaces to tabs.</para>

<para><command>uniq</command> discards all but one of successive
identical lines.</para>

<para><command>unlink</command> removes the given file.</para>

<para><command>uptime</command> reports how long the system has been
running, how many users are logged on, and the system load averages.</para>

<para><command>users</command> reports the names of the users currently
logged on.</para>

<para><command>vdir</command> is the same as ls -l.</para>

<para><command>wc</command> reports the number of lines, words, and bytes
for each given file, and a total line when more than one file is given.</para>

<para><command>who</command> reports who is logged on.</para>

<para><command>whoami</command> reports the user name associated with the
current effective user ID.</para>

<para><command>yes</command> outputs 'y' or a given string repeatedly,
until killed.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Coreutils Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &coreutils-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Coreutils depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils, GCC,
Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Perl, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-dejagnu" xreflabel="DejaGnu">
<title>DejaGnu</title>
<?dbhtml filename="dejagnu.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch05-dejagnu"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>DejaGnu (1.4.3):
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/dejagnu/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of DejaGnu</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &dejagnu-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The DejaGnu package contains a framework for testing other programs.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed program</emphasis>: runtest</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short description</title>

<para><command>runtest</command> is the wrapper script that finds the proper
expect shell and then runs DejaGnu.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>DejaGnu Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &dejagnu-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Dejagnu depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-diffutils" xreflabel="Diffutils">
<title>Diffutils</title>
<?dbhtml filename="diffutils.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-diffutils"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Diffutils (2.8.1):
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/diffutils/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Diffutils</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &diffutils-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The programs from this package show you the differences between two
files or directories. It's most common use is to create software
patches.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: cmp, diff, diff3 and sdiff</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>cmp</command> compares two files and reports whether or
in which bytes they differ.</para>

<para><command>diff</command> compares two files or directories and reports
which lines in the files differ.</para>

<para><command>diff3</command> compares three files line by line.</para>

<para><command>sdiff</command> merges two files and interactively outputs
the results.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Diffutils Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &diffutils-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Diffutils depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils, GCC,
Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-e2fsprogs" xreflabel="E2fsprogs">
<title>E2fsprogs</title>
<?dbhtml filename="e2fsprogs.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-e2fsprogs"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>E2fsprogs (1.34):
<ulink url="ftp://download.sourceforge.net/pub/sourceforge/e2fsprogs/"/>
<ulink url="http://download.sourceforge.net/e2fsprogs/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of E2fsprogs</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &e2fsprogs-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>E2fsprogs provides the filesystem utilities for use with the
 ext2 filesystem. It also supports the ext3 filesystem with journaling
 support.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: badblocks, blkid, chattr,
compile_et, debugfs, dumpe2fs, e2fsck, e2image, e2label, findfs, fsck,
fsck.ext2, fsck.ext3, logsave, lsattr, mk_cmds, mke2fs, mkfs.ext2, mkfs.ext3,
mklost+found, resize2fs, tune2fs and uuidgen.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed libraries</emphasis>: libblkid.[a,so],
libcom_err.[a,so], libe2p.[a,so], libext2fs.[a,so], libss.[a,so] and
libuuid.[a,so]</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>badblocks</command> searches a device (usually a disk
partition) for bad blocks.</para>

<para><command>blkid</command> is a command line utility to locate and
print block device attributes.</para>

<para><command>chattr</command> changes the attributes of files on a
second extended (ext2) filesystem.</para>

<para><command>compile_et</command> is an error table compiler. It
converts a table of error-code names and messages into a C source file
suitable for use with the com_err library.</para>

<para><command>debugfs</command> is a filesystem debugger. It can be
used to examine and change the state of an ext2 filesystem.</para>

<para><command>dumpe2fs</command> prints the super block and blocks group
information for the filesystem present on a given device.</para>

<para><command>e2fsck</command> is used to check, and optionally repair,
second extended (ext2) filesystems, and also ext3 filesystems.</para>

<para><command>e2image</command> is used to save critical ext2 filesystem
data to a file.</para>

<para><command>e2label</command> will display or change the filesystem
label on the ext2 filesystem present on a given device.</para>

<para><command>findfs</command> finds a file system by label or UUID.</para>

<para><command>fsck</command> is used to check, and optionally repair,
filesystems. By default it checks the filesystems listed in
<filename>/etc/fstab</filename></para>

<para><command>logsave</command> saves the output of a command in a logfile.</para>

<para><command>lsattr</command> lists the attributes of files on a second
extended filesystem.</para>

<para><command>mk_cmds</command> converts a table of command names
and help messages into a C source file suitable for use with the
<filename>libss</filename> subsystem library.</para>

<para><command>mke2fs</command> is used to create a second extended
filesystem on the given device.</para>

<para><command>mklost+found</command> is used to create a
<filename>lost+found</filename> directory on a second extended filesystem.
It pre-allocates disk blocks to this directory to lighten the task of e2fsck.</para>

<para><command>resize2fs</command> can be used to enlarge or shrink an
ext2 filesystem.</para>

<para><command>tune2fs</command> is used adjust tunable filesystem
parameters on a second extended filesystem.</para>

<para><command>uuidgen</command> creates new universally unique
identifiers (UUID). Each new UUID can reasonably be considered unique
among all UUIDs created, on the local system and on other systems, in the
past and in the future.</para>

<para><command>libblkid</command> contains routines for device
identification and token extraction.</para>

<para><command>libcom_err</command> is the common error display routine.</para>

<para><command>libe2p</command> is used by dumpe2fs, chattr, and lsattr.</para>

<para><command>libext2fs</command> contains routines to enable user-level
programs to manipulate an ext2 filesystem.</para>

<para><command>libss</command> is used by debugfs.</para>

<para><command>libuuid</command> contains routines for generating unique
identifiers for objects that may be accessible beyond the local system.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>E2fsprogs Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &e2fsprogs-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>E2fsprogs depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils,
Diffutils, Gawk, GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed, Texinfo.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-ed" xreflabel="Ed">
<title>Ed</title>
<?dbhtml filename="ed.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-ed"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Ed (0.2): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/ed/"/>

Ed Mkstemp Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/ed-0.2-mkstemp.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Ed</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &ed-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>GNU ed is an 8-bit clean, POSIX-compliant line editor.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: ed and red (link to ed)</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>ed</command> is a line-oriented text editor. It can be used
to create, display, modify and otherwise manipulate text files.</para>

<para><command>red</command> is a restricted ed -- it can only edit files
in the current directory and cannot execute shell commands.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Ed Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &ed-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Ed depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils, GCC,
Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-expect" xreflabel="expect">
<title>Expect</title>
<?dbhtml filename="expect.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch05-expect"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Expect (5.39.0):
<ulink url="http://expect.nist.gov/src/"/>

Expect Spawn Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/expect-5.39.0-spawn.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Expect</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &expect-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Expect package provides a program that performs programmed dialogue
with other interactive programs.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed program</emphasis>: expect</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed library</emphasis>: libexpect5.39.a</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short description</title>

<para><command>expect</command> "talks" to other interactive programs according
to a script.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Expect Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &expect-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Expect depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed, Tcl.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-file" xreflabel="File">
<title>File</title>
<?dbhtml filename="file.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-file"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>File (4.06): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gw.com/mirrors/pub/unix/file/"/>

Alternate Download Location:
<ulink url="ftp://gaosu.rave.org/pub/linux/lfs/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of File</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &file-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>File is a utility used to determine file types.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed program</emphasis>: file</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed library</emphasis>: libmagic.[a,so]</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short description</title>

<para><command>file</command> tries to classify each given file. It does
this by performing several tests: filesystem tests, magic number tests, and
language tests. The first test that succeeds determines the result.</para>

<para><command>libmagic</command> contains routines for magic number
recognition, used by the file program.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>File Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &file-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>File depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed, Zlib.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-findutils" xreflabel="Findutils">
<title>Findutils</title>
<?dbhtml filename="findutils.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-findutils"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Findutils (4.3CR20):
<ulink url="ftp://alpha.gnu.org/gnu/findutils/"/></literallayout>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Findutils</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &findutils-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Findutils package contains programs to find files, either
on-the-fly (by doing a live recursive search through directories and only
showing files that match the specifications) or by searching through a
database.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: bigram, code, find, frcode,
locate, updatedb and xargs</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>bigram</command> was formerly used to produce locate
databases.</para>

<para><command>code</command> was formerly used to produce locate
databases. It is the ancestor of frcode.</para>

<para><command>find</command> searches given directory trees for files
matching the specified criteria.</para>

<para><command>frcode</command> is called by updatedb to compress the
list of file names. It uses front-compression, reducing the database size by a
factor of 4 to 5.</para>

<para><command>locate</command> searches through a database of file names,
and reports the names that contain a given string or match a given pattern.</para>

<para><command>updatedb</command> updates the locate database. It scans
the entire filesystem (including other filesystems that are currently mounted,
unless told not to) and puts every file name it finds in the database.</para>

<para><command>xargs</command> can be used to apply a given command to
a list of files.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Findutils Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &findutils-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Findutils depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils,
Diffutils, GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-flex" xreflabel="Flex">
<title>Flex</title>
<?dbhtml filename="flex.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-flex"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Flex (2.5.4a): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/non-gnu/flex/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Flex</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &flex-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Flex package is used to generate programs which recognize
patterns in text.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: flex, flex++ (link to flex)
and lex</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed library</emphasis>: libfl.a</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>flex</command> is a tool for generating programs that
recognize patterns in text. Pattern recognition is useful in many applications.
From a set of rules on what to look for flex makes a program that looks for
those patterns. The reason to use flex is that it is much easier to specify
the rules for than to write the actual pattern-finding program.</para>

<para><command>flex++</command> invokes a version of flex that is used
exclusively for C++ scanners.</para>

<para><command>libfl.a</command> is the flex library.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Flex Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &flex-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Flex depends on: Bash, Binutils, Bison, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, M4, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-gawk" xreflabel="Gawk">
<title>Gawk</title>
<?dbhtml filename="gawk.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-gawk"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Gawk (3.1.3): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/pub/gnu/gawk/"/>

Gawk Libexecdir Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/gawk-3.1.3-libexecdir.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Gawk</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &gawk-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Gawk is an awk implementation that is used to manipulate text
files.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: awk (link to gawk), gawk,
gawk-3.1.3, grcat, igawk, pgawk, pgawk-3.1.3 and pwcat</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>gawk</command> is a program for manipulating text files.
It is the GNU implementation of awk.</para>

<para><command>grcat</command> dumps the group database
<filename>/etc/group</filename>.</para>

<para><command>igawk</command> gives gawk the ability to
include files.</para>

<para><command>pgawk</command> is the profiling version of gawk.</para>

<para><command>pwcat</command> dumps the password database
<filename>/etc/passwd</filename>.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Gawk Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &gawk-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Gawk depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils,
Diffutils, GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-gcc" xreflabel="GCC">
<title>GCC</title>
<?dbhtml filename="gcc.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-gcc"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>GCC (3.3.2): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/pub/gnu/gcc/"/>

GCC No-Fixincludes Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/gcc-3.3.2-no_fixincludes-1.patch"/>

GCC Specs Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/gcc-3.3.2-specs-1.patch"/>

GCC-2 (2.95.3): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/pub/gnu/gcc/"/>

GCC-2 Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/gcc-2.95.3-2.patch"/>

GCC-2 No-Fixincludes Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/gcc-2.95.3-no-fixinc.patch"/>

GCC-2 Return-Type Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/gcc-2.95.3-returntype-fix.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of GCC</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &gcc-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The GCC package contains the GNU compiler collection, including
the C and C++ compilers.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: c++, cc (link to gcc),
cc1, cc1plus, collect2, cpp, g++, gcc, gccbug, and gcov</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed libraries</emphasis>: libgcc.a, libgcc_eh.a,
libgcc_s.so, libstdc++.[a,so] and libsupc++.a</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>cpp</command> is the C preprocessor. It is used by the
compiler to have the #include and #define and such statements expanded in
the source files.</para>

<para><command>g++</command> is the C++ compiler.</para>

<para><command>gcc</command> is the C compiler. It is used to translate
the source code of a program into assembly code.</para>

<para><command>gccbug</command> is a shell script used to help create
good bug reports.</para>

<para><command>gcov</command> is a coverage testing tool. It is used to
analyze programs to find out where optimizations will have the most effect.</para>

<para><command>libgcc*</command> contains run-time support for gcc.</para>

<para><command>libstdc++</command> is the standard C++ library. It contains
many frequently-used functions.</para>

<para><command>libsupc++</command> provides supporting routines
for the c++ programming language.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>GCC Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &gcc-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>GCC depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils, Findutils,
Gawk, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Perl, Sed, Texinfo.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-gettext" xreflabel="Gettext">
<title>Gettext</title>
<?dbhtml filename="gettext.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-gettext"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Gettext (0.13.1): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/gettext/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Gettext</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &gettext-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Gettext package is used for internationalization and
localization. Programs can be compiled with Native Language Support
(NLS) which enable them to output messages in the user's native
language.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: autopoint, config.charset,
config.rpath, envsubst, gettext, gettextize, hostname, msgattrib, msgcat, msgcmp,
msgcomm, msgconv, msgen, msgexec, msgfilter, msgfmt, msggrep, msginit,
msgmerge, msgunfmt, msguniq, ngettext, project-id, team-address, trigger,
urlget, user-email and xgettext</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed libraries</emphasis>: libasprintf[a,so],
libgettextlib[a,so], libgettextpo[a,so] and libgettextsrc[a,so]</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>autopoint</command> copies standard gettext infrastructure
files into a source package.</para>

<para><command>config.charset</command> outputs a system-dependent table of
character encoding aliases.</para>

<para><command>config.rpath</command> outputs a system-dependent set of
variables, describing how to set the runtime search path of shared libraries in an
executable.</para>

<para><command>envsubst</command> substitutes environment variables in shell
format strings.</para>

<para><command>gettext</command> translates a natural language message into
the user's language, by looking up the translation in a message catalog.</para>

<para><command>gettextize</command> copies all standard Gettext files into
the given top-level directory of a package, to begin internationalizing it.</para>

<para><command>hostname</command> displays a network hostname in various
forms.</para>

<para><command>msgattrib</command> filters the messages of a translation
catalog according to their attributes and manipulates the attributes.</para>

<para><command>msgcat</command> concatenates and merges the given
<filename>.po</filename> files.</para>

<para><command>msgcmp</command> compares two <filename>.po</filename>
files to check that both contain the same set of msgid strings.</para>

<para><command>msgcomm</command> finds the messages that are common to
to the given <filename>.po</filename> files.</para>

<para><command>msgconv</command> converts a translation catalog to a
different character encoding.</para>

<para><command>msgen</command> creates an English translation catalog.</para>

<para><command>msgexec</command> applies a command to all translations of a
translation catalog.</para>

<para><command>msgfilter</command> applies a filter to all translations of a
translation catalog.</para>

<para><command>msgfmt</command> generates a binary message catalog from
from a translation catalog.</para>

<para><command>msggrep</command> extracts all messages of a translation
catalog that match a given pattern or belong to some given source files.</para>

<para><command>msginit</command> creates a new  <filename>.po</filename>
file, initializing the meta information with values from the user's
environment.</para>

<para><command>msgmerge</command> combines two raw translations into a
single file.</para>

<para><command>msgunfmt</command> decompiles a binary message catalog
into raw translation text.</para>

<para><command>msguniq</command> unifies duplicate translations in a
translation catalog.</para>

<para><command>ngettext</command> displays native language translations of a
textual message whose grammatical form depends on a number.</para>

<para><command>xgettext</command> extracts the translatable message lines
from the given source files, to make the first translation template.</para>

<para><command>libasprintf</command> defines the autosprintf class which
makes C formatted output routines usable in C++ programs, for use with the
&lt;string&gt; strings and the &lt;iostream&gt; streams.</para>

<para><command>libgettextlib</command> is a private library containing
common routines used by the various gettext programs. They're not meant for
general use.</para>

<para><command>libgettextpo</command> is used to write specialized
programs that process PO files. This library is used when the standard
applications shipped with gettext won't suffice (such as msgcomm, msgcmp,
msgattrib and msgen).</para>

<para><command>libgettextsrc</command> is a private library containing
common routines used by the various gettext programs. They're not meant for
general use.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Gettext Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &gettext-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Gettext depends on: Bash, Binutils, Bison, Coreutils,
Diffutils, Gawk, GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-glibc" xreflabel="Glibc">
<title>Glibc</title>
<?dbhtml filename="glibc.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-glibc"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Glibc (2.3.2): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/glibc/"/>

Glibc-linuxthreads (2.3.2): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/glibc/"/>

Glibc Sscanf Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/glibc-2.3.2-sscanf-1.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Glibc</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &glibc-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Glibc is the C library that provides the system calls and basic
functions such as open, malloc, printf, etc. The C library is used by all
dynamically linked programs.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: catchsegv, gencat, getconf,
getent, glibcbug, iconv, iconvconfig, ldconfig, ldd, lddlibc4, locale,
localedef, mtrace, nscd, nscd_nischeck, pcprofiledump, pt_chown, rpcgen,
rpcinfo, sln, sprof, tzselect, xtrace, zdump and zic</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed libraries</emphasis>: ld.so, libBrokenLocale.[a,so],
libSegFault.so, libanl.[a,so], libbsd-compat.a, libc.[a,so], libc_nonshared.a,
libcrypt.[a,so], libdl.[a,so], libg.a, libieee.a, libm.[a,so], libmcheck.a,
libmemusage.so, libnsl.a, libnss_compat.so, libnss_dns.so, libnss_files.so,
libnss_hesiod.so, libnss_nis.so, libnss_nisplus.so, libpcprofile.so,
libpthread.[a,so], libresolv.[a,so], librpcsvc.a, librt.[a,so], libthread_db.so
and libutil.[a,so]</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>catchsegv</command> can be used to create a stack trace
when a program terminates with a segmentation fault.</para>

<para><command>gencat</command> generates message catalogues.</para>

<para><command>getconf</command> displays the system configuration values
for filesystem specific variables.</para>

<para><command>getent</command> gets entries from an administrative
database.</para>

<para><command>glibcbug</command> creates a bug report and mails it to the
bug email address.</para>

<para><command>iconv</command> performs character set conversion.</para>

<para><command>iconvconfig</command> creates fastloading iconv module
configuration file.</para>

<para><command>ldconfig</command> configures the dynamic linker runtime
bindings.</para>

<para><command>ldd</command> reports which shared libraries are required
by each given program or shared library.</para>

<para><command>lddlibc4</command> assists ldd with object files.</para>

<para><command>locale</command> is a Perl program that tells the compiler
to enable or disable the use of POSIX locales for built-in operations.</para>

<para><command>localedef</command> compiles locale specifications.</para>

<para><command>mtrace</command>...</para>

<para><command>nscd</command> is a name service cache daemon providing a
cache for the most common name service requests.</para>

<para><command>nscd_nischeck</command> checks whether or not secure mode
is necessary for NIS+ lookup.</para>

<para><command>pcprofiledump</command> dumps information generated by
PC profiling.</para>

<para><command>pt_chown</command> is a helper program for grantpt to set
the owner, group and access permissions of a slave pseudo terminal.</para>

<para><command>rpcgen</command> generates C code to implement the
RPC protocol.</para>

<para><command>rpcinfo</command> makes an RPC call to an RPC server.</para>

<para><command>sln</command> is used to make symbolic links. The program
is statically linked, so it is useful for making symbolic links to dynamic
libraries if the dynamic linking system for some reason is nonfunctional.</para>

<para><command>sprof</command> reads and displays shared object profiling
data.</para>

<para><command>tzselect</command> asks the user about the location of the
system and reports the corresponding time zone description.</para>

<para><command>xtrace</command> traces the execution of a program by
printing the currently executed function.</para>

<para><command>zdump</command> is the time zone dumper.</para>

<para><command>zic</command> is the time zone compiler.</para>

<para><command>ld.so</command> is the helper program for shared library
executables.</para>

<para><command>libBrokenLocale</command> is used by programs, such as
Mozilla, to solve broken locales.</para>

<para><command>libSegFault</command> is a segmentation fault signal
handler. It tries to catch segfaults.</para>

<para><command>libanl</command> is an asynchronous name lookup
library.</para>

<para><command>libbsd-compat</command> provides the portability needed
in order to run certain BSD programs under Linux.</para>

<para><command>libc</command> is the main C library -- a collection of
commonly used functions.</para>

<para><command>libcrypt</command> is the cryptography library.</para>

<para><command>libdl</command> is the dynamic linking interface library.</para>

<para><command>libg</command> is a runtime library for g++.</para>

<para><command>libieee</command> is the IEEE floating point library.</para>

<para><command>libm</command> is the mathematical library.</para>

<para><command>libmcheck</command> contains code run at boot.</para>

<para><command>libmemusage</command> is used by memusage to help collect
information about the memory usage of a program.</para>

<para><command>libnsl</command> is the network services library.</para>

<para><command>libnss*</command> are the Name Service Switch libraries,
containing functions for resolving host names, user names, group names,
aliases, services, protocols,and the like.</para>

<para><command>libpcprofile</command> contains profiling functions used
to track the amount of CPU time spent in which source code lines.</para>

<para><command>libpthread</command> is the POSIX threads library.</para>

<para><command>libresolv</command> contains functions for creating,
sending, and interpreting packets to the Internet domain name servers.</para>

<para><command>librpcsvc</command>contains functions providing
miscellaneous RPC services.</para>

<para><command>librt</command> contains functions providing most of the
interfaces specified by the POSIX.1b Realtime Extension.</para>

<para><command>libthread_db</command> contains functions useful for
building debuggers for multi-threaded programs.</para>

<para><command>libutil</command> contains code for "standard" functions
used in many different Unix utilities.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Glibc Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &glibc-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Glibc depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
Gawk, GCC, Gettext, Grep, Make, Perl, Sed, Texinfo.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-grep" xreflabel="Grep">
<title>Grep</title>
<?dbhtml filename="grep.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-grep"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Grep (2.5.1): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/grep/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Grep</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &grep-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Grep is a program used to print lines from a file matching a
specified pattern.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: egrep (link to grep), fgrep
(link to grep) and grep</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>egrep</command> prints lines matching an extended regular
expression.</para>

<para><command>fgrep</command> prints lines matching a list of fixed
strings.</para>

<para><command>grep</command> prints lines matching a basic regular
expression.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Grep Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &grep-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Grep depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils,
Diffutils, GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Make, Sed, Texinfo.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-groff" xreflabel="Groff">
<title>Groff</title>
<?dbhtml filename="groff.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-groff"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Groff (1.19): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/groff/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Groff</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &groff-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Groff package includes several text processing programs
for text formatting. Groff translates standard text and special
commands into formatted output, such as what you see in a manual
page.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: addftinfo, afmtodit, eqn,
eqn2graph, geqn (link to eqn), grn, grodvi, groff, groffer, grog, grolbp,
grolj4, grops, grotty, gtbl (link to tbl), hpftodit, indxbib, lkbib,
lookbib, mmroff, neqn, nroff, pfbtops, pic, pic2graph, post-grohtml,
pre-grohtml, refer, soelim, tbl, tfmtodit, troff and zsoelim (link to
soelim)</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>addftinfo</command> reads a troff font file and adds some
additional font-metric information that is used by the groff system.</para>

<para><command>afmtodit</command> creates a font file for use with
groff and grops.</para>

<para><command>eqn</command> compiles descriptions of equations embedded
within troff input files into commands that are understood by troff.</para>

<para><command>eqn2graph</command> converts an EQN equation into a cropped
image.</para>

<para><command>grn</command> is a groff preprocessor for gremlin files.</para>

<para><command>grodvi</command> is a driver for groff that produces TeX dvi format.</para>

<para><command>groff</command> is a front-end to the groff document
formatting system. Normally it runs the troff program and a post-processor
appropriate for the selected device.</para>

<para><command>groffer</command> displays groff files and man pages on X
and tty.</para>
<para><command>grog</command> reads files and guesses which of the groff
options -e, -man, -me, -mm, -ms, -p, -s, and -t are required for printing
files, and reports the groff command including those options.</para>

<para><command>grolbp</command> is a groff driver for Canon CAPSL printers
(LBP-4 and LBP-8 series laser printers).</para>

<para><command>grolj4</command> is a driver for groff that produces output
in PCL5 format suitable for an HP Laserjet 4 printer.</para>

<para><command>grops</command> translates the output of GNU troff to
Postscript.</para>

<para><command>grotty</command> translates the output of GNU troff into
a form suitable for typewriter-like devices.</para>

<para><command>gtbl</command> is the GNU implementation of tbl.</para>

<para><command>hpftodit</command> creates a font file for use with
groff -Tlj4 from an HP-tagged font metric file.</para>

<para><command>indxbib</command> makes an inverted index for the
bibliographic databases a specified file for use with refer, lookbib,
and lkbib.</para>

<para><command>lkbib</command> searches bibliographic databases for
references that contain specified keys and reports any references found.</para>

<para><command>lookbib</command> prints a prompt on the standard error
(unless the standard input is not a terminal), reads from the standard input
a line containing a set of keywords, searches the bibliographic databases in
a specified file for references containing those keywords, prints any
references found on the standard output and repeats this process until the
end of input.</para>

<para><command>mmroff</command> is a simple preprocessor for groff.</para>

<para><command>neqn</command> formats equations for ascii output.</para>

<para><command>nroff</command> is a script that emulates the nroff command
using groff.</para>

<para><command>pfbtops</command> translates a Postscript font in .pfb
format to ASCII.</para>

<para><command>pic</command> compiles descriptions of pictures embedded
within troff or TeX input files into commands understood by TeX or troff.</para>

<para><command>pic2graph</command> converts a PIC diagram into a cropped
image.</para>

<para><command>pre-grohtml </command> translates  the output of GNU troff
to html.</para>

<para><command>post-grohtml</command> translates the output of GNU troff
to html.</para>

<para><command>refer</command> copies the contents of a file to the
standard output, except that lines between .[ and .] are interpreted as
citations, and lines between .R1 and .R2 are interpreted as commands about
how citations are to be processed.</para>

<para><command>soelim</command> reads files and replaces lines of the form
<emphasis>.so file</emphasis> by the contents of the mentioned
<emphasis>file</emphasis>.</para>

<para><command>tbl</command> compiles descriptions of tables embedded
within troff input files into commands that are understood by troff.</para>

<para><command>tfmtodit</command> creates a font file for use with
groff -Tdvi.</para>

<para><command>troff</command> is highly compatible with Unix troff.
Usually it should be invoked using the groff command, which will also run
preprocessors and post-processors in the appropriate order and with the
appropriate options.</para>

<para><command>zsoelim</command> is the GNU implementation of soelim.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Groff Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &groff-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Groff depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
Gawk, GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-grub" xreflabel="Grub">
<title>Grub</title>
<?dbhtml filename="grub.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-grub"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Grub (0.93):
<ulink url="ftp://alpha.gnu.org/pub/gnu/grub/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Grub</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &grub-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Grub package contains a bootloader.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: grub, grub-install,
grub-md5-crypt, grub-terminfo and mbchk</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>grub</command> is the GRand Unified Bootloader's command
shell.</para>

<para><command>grub-install</command> installs GRUB on the given device.</para>

<para><command>grub-md5-crypt</command> encrypts a password in MD5
format.</para>

<para><command>grub-terminfo</command> generates a terminfo command from a
terminfo name. It can be used if you have an uncommon terminal.</para>

<para><command>mbchk</command> checks the format of a multiboot kernel.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Grub Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &grub-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Grub depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Ncurses, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-gzip" xreflabel="Gzip">
<title>Gzip</title>
<?dbhtml filename="gzip.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-gzip"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Gzip (1.3.5): 
<ulink url="ftp://alpha.gnu.org/gnu/gzip/"/></literallayout>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Gzip</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &gzip-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Gzip package contains programs to compress and decompress files
using the Lempel-Ziv coding (LZ77).</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: gunzip (link to gzip), gzexe,
gzip, uncompress (link to gunzip), zcat (link to gzip), zcmp, zdiff,
zegrep, zfgrep, zforce, zgrep, zless, zmore and znew</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>gunzip</command> decompresses gzipped files.</para>

<para><command>gzexe</command> is used to create self-uncompressing
executable files.</para>

<para><command>gzip</command> compresses the given files, using
Lempel-Ziv (LZ77) coding.</para>

<para><command>zcat</command> uncompresses the given gzipped files to
standard output.</para>

<para><command>zcmp</command> runs cmp on gzipped files.</para>

<para><command>zdiff</command> runs diff on gzipped files.</para>

<para><command>zegrep</command> runs egrep on gzipped files.</para>

<para><command>zfgrep</command> runs fgrep on gzipped files.</para>

<para><command>zforce</command> forces a .gz extension on all given files
that are gzipped files, so that gzip will not compress them again. This can be
useful when file names were truncated during a file transfer.</para>

<para><command>zgrep</command> runs grep on gzipped files.</para>

<para><command>zless</command> runs less on gzipped files.</para>

<para><command>zmore</command> runs more on gzipped files.</para>

<para><command>znew</command> recompresses files from compress format
to gzip format -- .Z to .gz.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Gzip Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &gzip-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Gzip depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-inetutils" xreflabel="Inetutils">
<title>Inetutils</title>
<?dbhtml filename="inetutils.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-inetutils"/>.</para>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Inetutils (1.4.2):
<ulink url="http://freshmeat.net/projects/inetutils/"/>

Inetutils No-Server-Man-Pages Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/inetutils-1.4.2-no_server_man_pages-1.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Contents of Inetutils</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &inetutils-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Inetutils package contains network clients and servers.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: ftp, ping, rcp, rlogin, rsh,
talk, telnet and tftp</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>ftp</command> is the ARPANET file transfer program.</para>

<para><command>ping</command> sends echo-request packets and reports how
long the replies take.</para>

<para><command>rcp</command> does remote file copy.</para>

<para><command>rlogin</command> does remote login.</para>

<para><command>rsh</command> runs a remote shell.</para>

<para><command>talk</command> is used to chat up another user.</para>

<para><command>telnet</command> is an interface to the TELNET protocol.</para>

<para><command>tftp</command> is a trivial file transfer program.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Inetutils Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &inetutils-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Inetutils depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils,
Diffutils, GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Ncurses, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>

<sect1 id="aa-kbd" xreflabel="Kbd">
<title>Kbd</title>
<?dbhtml filename="kbd.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-kbd"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Kbd (1.08): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.win.tue.nl/pub/linux-local/utils/kbd/"/>

Kbd More-Programs Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/kbd-1.08-more-programs-3.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Kbd</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &kbd-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Kbd contains keytable files and keyboard utilities.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: chvt, deallocvt, dumpkeys,
fgconsole, getkeycodes, getunimap, kbd_mode, kbdrate, loadkeys, loadunimap,
mapscrn, openvt, psfaddtable (link to psfxtable), psfgettable (link to
psfxtable), psfstriptable (link to psfxtable), psfxtable, resizecons,
setfont, setkeycodes, setleds, setlogcons, setmetamode, setvesablank,
showconsolefont, showkey, unicode_start and unicode_stop</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>chvt</command> changes the foreground virtual terminal.</para>

<para><command>deallocvt</command> deallocates unused virtual terminals.</para>

<para><command>dumpkeys</command> dumps the keyboard translation tables.</para>

<para><command>fgconsole</command> prints the number of the active virtual terminal.</para>

<para><command>getkeycodes</command> prints the kernel scancode-to-keycode
mapping table.</para>

<para><command>getunimap</command> prints the currently used unimap.</para>

<para><command>kbd_mode</command> reports or sets the keyboard mode.</para>

<para><command>kbdrate</command> sets the keyboard repeat and delay rates.</para>

<para><command>loadkeys</command> loads the keyboard translation tables.</para>

<para><command>loadunimap</command> loads the kernel unicode-to-font mapping table.</para>

<para><command>mapscrn</command> is an obsolete program that used to load
a user-defined output character mapping table into the console driver. This is
now done by setfont.</para>

<para><command>openvt</command> starts a program on a new virtual terminal (VT).</para>

<para><command>psf*</command> are a set of tools for handling Unicode
character tables for console fonts.</para>

<para><command>resizecons</command> changes the kernel idea of the console size.</para>

<para><command>setfont</command> lets you change the EGA/VGA fonts on the console.</para>

<para><command>setkeycodes</command> loads kernel scancode-to-keycode
mapping table entries, useful if you have some unusual keys on your keyboard.</para>

<para><command>setleds</command> sets the keyboard flags and LEDs. Many
people find it useful to have NumLock on by default, setleds +num achieves this.</para>

<para><command>setlogcons</command> sends kernel messages to the console.</para>

<para><command>setmetamode</command> defines the keyboard meta key handling.</para>

<para><command>setvesablank</command> lets you fiddle with the built-in
hardware screensaver (no toasters, just a blank screen).</para>

<para><command>showconsolefont</command> shows the current EGA/VGA console
screen font.</para>

<para><command>showkey</command> reports the scancodes and keycodes and
ASCII codes of the keys pressed on the keyboard.</para>

<para><command>unicode_start</command> puts the keyboard and console in
unicode mode.</para>

<para><command>unicode_stop</command> reverts keyboard and console from
unicode mode.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Kbd Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &kbd-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Kbd depends on: Bash, Binutils, Bison, Coreutils,
Diffutils, Flex, GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Gzip, M4, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-less" xreflabel="Less">
<title>Less</title>
<?dbhtml filename="less.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-less"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Less (381): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/less/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Less</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &less-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Less is a file pager, or text viewer. It displays the contents
of a file, or stream, and has the ability to scroll. Less has a few
features not included in the <userinput>more</userinput> pager,
such as the ability to scroll backwards.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: less, lessecho and lesskey</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>less</command> is a file viewer or pager. It displays the
contents of the given file, letting you scroll around, find strings, and jump
to marks.</para>

<para><command>lessecho</command> is needed to expand metacharacters,
such as * and ?, in filenames on Unix systems.</para>

<para><command>lesskey</command> is used to specify the key bindings
for less.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Less Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &less-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Less depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Ncurses, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-bootscripts" xreflabel="LFS-Bootscripts">
<title>LFS-Bootscripts</title>
<?dbhtml filename="bootscripts.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-lfs-bootscripts"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>LFS-Bootscripts (1.12): 
<ulink url="http://downloads.linuxfromscratch.org/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of LFS-bootscripts</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &bootscripts-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The LFS-Bootscripts package contains SysV init style shell
scripts. These scripts do various tasks such as check filesystem
integrity during boot, load keymaps, set up networks and halt
processes at shutdown.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed scripts</emphasis>: checkfs, cleanfs, functions,
halt, ifdown, ifup, loadkeys, localnet, mountfs, mountproc, network, rc,
reboot, sendsignals, setclock, swap, sysklogd and template</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para>The <command>checkfs</command> script checks the file systems just
before they are mounted (with the exception of journal and network based file
systems).</para>

<para>The <command>cleanfs</command> script removes files that shouldn't be
preserved between reboots, such as those in <filename>/var/run/</filename> and
<filename>/var/lock/</filename>. It re-creates <filename>/var/run/utmp</filename>
and removes the possibly present <filename>/etc/nologin</filename>,
<filename>/fastboot</filename> and <filename>/forcefsck</filename> files.</para>

<para>The <command>functions</command> script contains functions shared among
different scripts, such as error and status checking.</para>

<para>The <command>halt</command> script halts the system.</para>

<para>The <command>ifdown</command> and <command>ifup</command> scripts assist
the network script with network devices.</para>

<para>The <command>loadkeys</command> script loads the keymap table you
specified as proper for your keyboard layout.</para>

<para>The <command>localnet</command> script sets up the system's hostname and
local loopback device.</para>

<para>The <command>mountfs</command> script mounts all file systems that
aren't marked noauto or aren't network based.</para>

<para>The <command>mountproc</command> script is used to mount the proc
filesystem.</para>

<para>The <command>network</command> script sets up network interfaces, such
as network cards, and sets up the default gateway where applicable.</para>

<para>The <command>rc</command> script is the master runlevel control script.
It is responsible for running all the other scripts one-by-one in a specific
sequence.</para>

<para>The <command>reboot</command> script reboots the system.</para>

<para>The <command>sendsignals</command> script makes sure every process is
terminated before the system reboots or halts.</para>

<para>The <command>setclock</command> script resets the kernel clock to
localtime in case the hardware clock isn't set to GMT time.</para>

<para>The <command>swap</command> script enables and disables swap files and
partitions.</para>

<para>The <command>sysklogd</command> script starts and stops the system and
kernel log daemons.</para>

<para>The <command>template</command> script is a template you can use to
create your own bootscripts for your other daemons.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>LFS-Bootscripts Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &bootscripts-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>LFS-Bootscripts depends on: Bash, Coreutils.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-lfs-utils" xreflabel="Lfs-Utils">
<title>Lfs-Utils</title>
<?dbhtml filename="lfs-utils.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-lfs-utils"/>.</para>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Lfs-utils (0.4.2):
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/~winkie/downloads/lfs-utils/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Contents of Lfs-Utils</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &lfs-utils-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Lfs-Utils package contains some miscellaneous programs used by
various packages, but are not large enough to warrant their own
individual package.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: mktemp, tempfile, http-get
and iana-net</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed files</emphasis>: protocols, services</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>mktemp</command> creates temporary files in a secure manner.
It is used in scripts.</para>

<para><command>tempfile</command> creates temporary files in a less secure
manner than <userinput>mktemp</userinput>. It is installed for
backwards-compatibility.</para>

<para>The <command>http-get</command> script takes advantage of a little known
feature of <userinput>bash</userinput> called "net redirection". It is used to
download from websites without using any other programs.</para>

<para><command>iana-net</command> uses the <userinput>http-get</userinput>
script to simplify the process of procuring IANA's services and protocols
configuration files.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Lfs-Utils Installation Dependencies</title>

<literallayout>(No dependencies checked yet.)</literallayout>
</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-libtool" xreflabel="Libtool">
<title>Libtool</title>
<?dbhtml filename="libtool.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-libtool"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Libtool (1.5): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/libtool/"/></literallayout>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Libtool</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &libtool-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>GNU libtool is a generic library support script. Libtool hides
  the complexity of using shared libraries behind a consistent,
  portable interface.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: libtool and libtoolize</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed libraries</emphasis>: libltdl.[a,so].</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>libtool</command> provides generalized library-building
support services.</para>

<para><command>libtoolize</command> provides a standard way to add
libtool support to a package.</para>

<para><command>libltdl</command> hides the various difficulties of
dlopening libraries.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Libtool Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &libtool-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Libtool depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-kernel" xreflabel="Linux">
<title>Linux (the kernel)</title>
<?dbhtml filename="kernel.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch08-kernel"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Linux (2.4.23):
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.kernel.org/pub/linux/kernel/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Linux</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &kernel-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Linux kernel is at the core of every Linux system. It's what makes
Linux tick. When a computer is turned on and boots a Linux system, the
very first piece of Linux software that gets loaded is the kernel. The
kernel initializes the system's hardware components: serial ports, parallel
ports, sound cards, network cards, IDE controllers, SCSI controllers and a
lot more. In a nutshell the kernel makes the hardware available so that the
software can run.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed files</emphasis>: the kernel and the kernel
headers</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para>The <emphasis>kernel</emphasis> is the engine of your GNU/Linux system.
When switching on your box, the kernel is the first part of your operating
system that gets loaded. It detects and initializes all the components of your
computer's hardware, then makes these components available as a tree of files
to the software, and turns a single CPU into a multi-tasking machine capable
of running scores of programs seemingly at the same time.</para>
                                                            
<para>The <emphasis>kernel headers</emphasis> define the interface to the
services that the kernel provides. The headers in your system's
<filename>include</filename> directory should <emphasis>always</emphasis> be
the ones against which Glibc was compiled and should therefore
<emphasis>not</emphasis> be replaced when upgrading the kernel.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Linux Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &kernel-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Linux depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Findutils,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Gzip, Make, Modutils, Perl, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-m4" xreflabel="M4">
<title>M4</title>
<?dbhtml filename="m4.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-m4"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>M4 (1.4): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/m4/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of M4</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &m4-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>M4 is a macro processor. It copies input to output, expanding
macros as it goes. Macros are either built-in or user-defined and can
take any number of arguments. Besides just doing macro expansion, m4
has built-in functions for including named files, running Unix
commands, doing integer arithmetic, manipulating text in various ways,
recursion, etc. The m4 program can be used either as a front-end to a
compiler or as a macro processor in its own right.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed program</emphasis>: m4</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>m4</command> copies the given files
while expanding the macros that they contain. These macros are either built-in
or user-defined and can take any number of arguments. Besides just doing macro
expansion, m4 has built-in functions for including named files, running Unix
commands, doing integer arithmetic, manipulating text in various ways,
recursion, and so on. The m4 program can be used either as a front-end to a
compiler or as a macro processor in its own right.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>M4 Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &m4-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>M4 depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils, GCC,
Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Perl, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-make" xreflabel="Make">
<title>Make</title>
<?dbhtml filename="make.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-make"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Make (3.80): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/make/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Make</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &make-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Make determines, automatically, which pieces of a large program need
to be recompiled and issues the commands to recompile them.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed program</emphasis>: make</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short description</title>

<para><command>make</command> automatically determines which pieces of a
large package need to be recompiled, and then issues the relevant commands.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Make Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &make-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Make depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-makedev" xreflabel="Makedev">
<title>MAKEDEV</title>
<?dbhtml filename="makedev.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-MAKEDEV"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>MAKEDEV (1.7):
<ulink url="http://downloads.linuxfromscratch.org/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of MAKEDEV</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &makedev-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The MAKEDEV script creates the static device nodes which
usually reside in the <filename class="directory">/dev</filename>
directory. Detailed information about device nodes may be found
in the <filename>Documentation/devices.txt</filename> file under
the Linux kernel source tree.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed script</emphasis>: MAKEDEV</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short description</title>

<para><command>MAKEDEV</command> is a script for creating the necessary
static device nodes, usually residing in the <filename>/dev</filename>
directory.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>MAKEDEV Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &makedev-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>MAKEDEV depends on: Bash, Coreutils.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-man" xreflabel="Man">
<title>Man</title>
<?dbhtml filename="man.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-man"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Man (1.5m2): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.win.tue.nl/pub/linux-local/utils/man/"/>

Man 80-Columns Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/man-1.5m2-80cols.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Man</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &man-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Man is a man pager.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: apropos, makewhatis, man,
man2dvi, man2html and whatis</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>apropos</command> searches the whatis database and displays
the short descriptions of system commands that contain a given string.</para>

<para><command>makewhatis</command> builds the whatis database. It reads
all the manual pages in the manpath and for each page writes the name and a
short description in the whatis database.</para>

<para><command>man</command> formats and displays the requested on-line
manual page.</para>

<para><command>man2dvi</command> converts a manual page into dvi format.</para>

<para><command>man2html</command> converts a manual page into html.</para>

<para><command>whatis</command> searches the whatis database and displays
the short descriptions of system commands that contain the given keyword as a
separate word.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Man Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &man-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Man depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Gawk, GCC,
Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-man-pages" xreflabel="Man-pages">
<title>Man-pages</title>
<?dbhtml filename="man-pages.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-man-pages"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Man-pages (1.64): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.kernel.org/pub/linux/docs/manpages/"/></literallayout>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Man-pages</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &man-pages-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Man-pages package contains over 1200 manual pages. This
documentation details the C and C++ functions, describes a few
important device files and provides documents which would otherwise
be missing from other packages.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed files</emphasis>: various manual pages</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short description</title>

<para>Examples of provided <emphasis>manual pages</emphasis> are the pages
describing all the C and C++ functions, important device files, and important
configuration files.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Man-pages Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &man-pages-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Man-pages depends on: Bash, Coreutils, Make.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-modutils" xreflabel="Modutils">
<title>Modutils</title>
<?dbhtml filename="modutils.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-modutils"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Modutils (2.4.26): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.kernel.org/pub/linux/utils/kernel/modutils/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Modutils</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &modutils-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Modutils package contains programs that you can use to work with
kernel modules.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: depmod, genksyms, insmod,
insmod_ksymoops_clean, kallsyms (link to insmod), kernelversion, ksyms
(link to insmod), lsmod (link to insmod), modinfo, modprobe (link to insmod)
and rmmod (link to insmod)</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>depmod</command> creates a dependency file, based on the
symbols it finds in the existing set of modules. This  dependency file is used
by modprobe to automatically load the required modules.</para>

<para><command>genksyms</command> generates symbol version information.</para>

<para><command>insmod</command> installs a loadable module in the running kernel.</para>

<para><command>insmod_ksymoops_clean</command> deletes saved ksyms and
modules not accessed for two days.</para>

<para><command>kallsyms</command> extracts all kernel symbols for debugging.</para>

<para><command>kernelversion</command> reports the major version of the
running kernel.</para>

<para><command>ksyms</command> displays exported kernel symbols.</para>

<para><command>lsmod</command> shows which modules are loaded.</para>

<para><command>modinfo</command> examines an object file associated with
a kernel module and displays any information that it can glean.</para>

<para><command>modprobe</command> uses a dependency file, created by
depmod, to automatically load the relevant modules.</para>

<para><command>rmmod</command> unloads modules from the running kernel.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Modutils Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &modutils-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Modutils depends on: Bash, Binutils, Bison, Coreutils,
Diffutils, Flex, GCC, Glibc, Grep, M4, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-ncurses" xreflabel="Ncurses">
<title>Ncurses</title>
<?dbhtml filename="ncurses.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-ncurses"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Ncurses (5.3): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/ncurses/"/>

Ncurses Etip Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/ncurses-5.3-etip-2.patch"/></literallayout>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Ncurses</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &ncurses-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Ncurses package provides character and terminal handling
libraries, including panels and menus.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: captoinfo (link to tic), clear,
infocmp, infotocap (link to tic), reset (link to tset), tack, tic, toe, tput
and tset</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed libraries</emphasis>: libcurses.[a,so] (link to
libncurses.[a,so]), libform.[a,so], libmenu.[a,so], libncurses++.a,
libncurses.[a,so], libpanel.[a,so]</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>captoinfo</command> converts a termcap description into a
terminfo description.</para>

<para><command>clear</command> clears the screen, if this is possible.</para>

<para><command>infocmp</command> compares or prints out terminfo
descriptions.</para>

<para><command>infotocap</command> converts a terminfo description into
a termcap description.</para>

<para><command>reset</command> reinitializes a terminal to its default
values.</para>

<para><command>tack</command> is the terminfo action checker. It is mainly
used to test the correctness of an entry in the terminfo database.</para>

<para><command>tic</command> is the terminfo entry-description compiler.
It translates a terminfo file from source format into the binary format needed
for the ncurses library routines. A terminfo file contains information on the
capabilities of a certain terminal.</para>

<para><command>toe</command> lists all available terminal types, for each
giving its primary name and its description.</para>

<para><command>tput</command> makes the values of terminal-dependent
capabilities available to the shell. It can also be used to reset or initialize
a terminal, or report its long name.</para>

<para><command>tset</command> can be used to initialize terminals.</para>

<para><command>libncurses*</command> contain functions to display text in
many complicated ways on a terminal screen. A good example of the use of these
functions is the menu displayed during the kernel's make menuconfig.</para>

<para><command>libform*</command> contain functions to implement forms.</para>

<para><command>libmenu*</command> contain functions to implement menus.</para>

<para><command>libpanel*</command> contain functions to implement panels.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Ncurses Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &ncurses-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Ncurses depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
Gawk, GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-net-tools" xreflabel="Net-tools">
<title>Net-tools</title>
<?dbhtml filename="net-tools.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-net-tools"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Net-tools (1.60): 
<ulink url="http://www.tazenda.demon.co.uk/phil/net-tools/"/>

Net-tools Mii-Tool-Gcc33 Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/net-tools-1.60-miitool-gcc33-1.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Net-tools</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &net-tools-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Net-tools package contains a collection of programs
which form the base of Linux networking.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: arp, dnsdomainname (link to
hostname), domainname (link to hostname), hostname, ifconfig, nameif, netstat,
nisdomainname (link to hostname), plipconfig, rarp, route, slattach and
ypdomainname (link to hostname)</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>arp</command> is used to manipulate the kernel's ARP cache,
usually to add or delete an entry, or to dump the entire cache.</para>

<para><command>dnsdomainname</command> reports the system's DNS domain
name.</para>

<para><command>domainname</command> reports or sets the system's NIS/YP
domain name.</para>

<para><command>hostname</command> reports or sets the name of the current
host system.</para>

<para><command>ifconfig</command> is the main utility for configuring
network interfaces.</para>

<para><command>nameif</command> names network interfaces based on MAC
addresses.</para>

<para><command>netstat</command> is used to report network connections,
routing tables, and interface statistics..</para>

<para><command>nisdomainname</command> does the same as domainname.</para>

<para><command>plipconfig</command> is used to fine tune the PLIP device
parameters, to improve its performance.</para>

<para><command>rarp</command> is used to manipulate the kernel's RARP
table.</para>

<para><command>route</command> is used to manipulate the IP routing
table.</para>

<para><command>slattach</command> attaches a network interface to a serial
line. This allows you to use normal terminal lines for point-to-point links to
other computers.</para>

<para><command>ypdomainname</command> does the same as domainname.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Net-tools Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &net-tools-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Net-tools depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, GCC,
Glibc, Make.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-patch" xreflabel="Patch">
<title>Patch</title>
<?dbhtml filename="patch.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-patch"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Patch (2.5.4): 
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/patch/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Patch</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &patch-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The patch program modifies a file according to a patch file. A patch
file usually is a list, created by the diff program, that contains
instructions on how an original file needs to be modified.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed program</emphasis>: patch</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short description</title>

<para><command>patch</command> modifies files according to a patch file.
A patch file normally is a difference listing created with the diff program.
By applying these differences to the original files, patch creates the patched
versions. Using patches instead a entire new tarballs to keep your sources
up-to-date can save you a lot of download time.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Patch Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &patch-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Patch depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-perl" xreflabel="Perl">
<title>Perl</title>
<?dbhtml filename="perl.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-perl"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Perl (5.8.2):
<ulink url="http://www.perl.com/"/>

Perl Libc Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/perl-5.8.2-libc-1.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Perl</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &perl-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Perl package contains perl, the Practical Extraction
and Report Language. Perl combines some of the best features of C,
sed, awk and sh into one powerful language.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: a2p, c2ph, dprofpp, enc2xs,
find2perl, h2ph, h2xs, libnetcfg, perl, perl5.8.2 (link to perl),
perlbug, perlcc, perldoc, perlivp, piconv, pl2pm, pod2html, pod2latex, pod2man,
pod2text, pod2usage, podchecker, podselect, psed (link to s2p), pstruct (link
to c2ph), s2p, splain and xsubpp</para> 

<para><emphasis>Installed libraries</emphasis>: (too many to name)</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>a2p</command> translates awk to perl.</para>

<para><command>c2ph</command> dumps C structures as generated from
"cc -g -S" stabs.</para>

<para><command>dprofpp</command> displays perl profile data.</para>

<para><command>en2cxs</command> builds a Perl extension for the Encode module,
from either Unicode Character Mappings or Tcl Encoding Files.</para>

<para><command>find2perl</command> translates find commands to perl.</para>

<para><command>h2ph</command> converts .h C header files to .ph Perl header files.</para>

<para><command>h2xs</command> converts .h C header files to Perl extensions.</para>

<para><command>libnetcfg</command> can be used to configure the libnet.</para>

<para><command>perl</command> combines some of the best features of C, sed,
awk and sh into a single swiss-army language.</para>

<para><command>perlbug</command> is used to generate bug reports about
Perl or the modules that come with it, and mail them.</para>

<para><command>perlcc</command> generates executables from Perl programs.</para>

<para><command>perldoc</command> displays a piece of documentation in pod
format that is embedded in the perl installation tree or in a perl script.</para>

<para><command>perlivp</command> is the Perl Installation Verification
Procedure. It can be used to verify that Perl and its libraries have been
installed correctly.</para>

<para><command>piconv</command> is a Perl version of the character encoding
converter <userinput>iconv</userinput>.</para>

<para><command>pl2pm</command> is a rough tool for converting Perl4 .pl
files to Perl5 .pm modules.</para>

<para><command>pod2html</command> converts files from pod format to HTML
format.</para>

<para><command>pod2latex</command> converts files from pod format to LaTeX
format.</para>

<para><command>pod2man</command> converts pod data to formatted *roff
input.</para>

<para><command>pod2text</command> converts pod data to formatted ASCII
text.</para>

<para><command>pod2usage</command> prints usage messages from embedded
pod docs in files.</para>

<para><command>podchecker</command> checks the syntax of pod format
documentation files.</para>

<para><command>podselect</command> displays selected sections of pod
documentation.</para>

<para><command>psed</command> is a Perl version of the stream editor
<userinput>sed</userinput>.</para>

<para><command>pstruct</command> dumps C structures as generated from
"cc -g -S" stabs.</para>

<para><command>s2p</command> translates sed to perl.</para>

<para><command>splain</command> is used to force verbose warning
diagnostics in perl.</para>

<para><command>xsubpp</command> converts Perl XS code into C code.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Perl Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &perl-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Perl depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
Gawk, GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-procinfo" xreflabel="Procinfo">
<title>Procinfo</title>
<?dbhtml filename="procinfo.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-procinfo"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Procinfo (18):
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.cistron.nl/pub/people/svm/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Procinfo</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &procinfo-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The procinfo program gathers system data, such as memory
usage and IRQ numbers, from the <filename>/proc</filename>
directory and formats this data in a meaningful way.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: lsdev, procinfo and
socklist</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>lsdev</command> lists the devices present in your system,
and which IRQs and IO ports they use.</para>

<para><command>procinfo</command> displays an overview of some of the info
present in the virtual proc filesystem.</para>

<para><command>socklist</command> lists the open sockets, reporting their
type, portnumber, and other specifics.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Procinfo Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &procinfo-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Procinfo depends on: Binutils, GCC, Glibc, Make, Ncurses.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-procps" xreflabel="Procps">
<title>Procps</title>
<?dbhtml filename="procps.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-procps"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Procps (3.1.14):
<ulink url="http://procps.sourceforge.net/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Procps</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &procps-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Procps package provides programs to monitor and
halt system processes. Procps gathers information about
processes via the <filename>/proc</filename> directory.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: free, kill, pgrep, pkill,
pmap, ps, skill, snice, sysctl, tload, top, uptime, vmstat, w and watch</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed library</emphasis>: libproc.so</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>free</command> reports the amount of free and used memory
in the system, both physical and swap memory.</para>

<para><command>kill</command> is used to send signals to processes.</para>

<para><command>pgrep</command> looks up processes based on their name
and other attributes.</para>

<para><command>pkill</command> signals processes based on their name
and other attributes.</para>

<para><command>pmap</command> reports the memory map of the given
process.</para>

<para><command>ps</command> gives a snapshot of the current processes.</para>

<para><command>skill</command> sends signals to processes matching the
given criteria.</para>

<para><command>snice</command> changes the scheduling priority of processes
matching the given criteria.</para>

<para><command>sysctl</command> modifies kernel parameters at run time.</para>

<para><command>tload</command> prints a graph of the current system load
average.</para>

<para><command>top</command> displays the top CPU processes. It provides
an ongoing look at processor activity in real time.</para>

<para><command>uptime</command> reports how long the system has been
running, how many users are logged on, and the system load averages.</para>

<para><command>vmstat</command> reports virtual memory statistics, giving
information about processes, memory, paging, block IO, traps, and CPU
activity.</para>

<para><command>w</command> shows which users are currently logged on,
where and since when.</para>

<para><command>watch</command> runs a given command repeatedly,
displaying the first screenful of its output. This allows you to watch the
output change over time.</para>

<para><command>libproc</command> contains the functions used by most
programs in this package.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Procps Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &procps-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Procps depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, GCC, Glibc,
Make, Ncurses.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-psmisc" xreflabel="Psmisc">
<title>Psmisc</title>
<?dbhtml filename="psmisc.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-psmisc"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Psmisc (21.4):
<ulink url="http://download.sourceforge.net/psmisc/"/>
<ulink url="ftp://download.sourceforge.net/pub/sourceforge/psmisc/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Psmisc</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &psmisc-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Psmisc package contains three programs which help
manage the <filename>/proc</filename> directory.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: fuser, killall, pstree and
pstree.x11 (link to pstree)</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>fuser</command> reports the PIDs of processes that use
the given files or filesystems.</para>

<para><command>killall</command> kills processes by name. It sends a signal
to all processes running any of the given commands.</para>

<para><command>pstree</command> displays running processes as a tree.</para>

<para><command>pstree.x11</command> same as pstree except that it waits for
confirmation before exiting.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Psmisc Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &psmisc-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Psmisc depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Ncurses, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-sed" xreflabel="Sed">
<title>Sed</title>
<?dbhtml filename="sed.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-sed"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Sed (4.0.8):
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/sed/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Sed</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &sed-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>sed is a stream editor. A stream editor is used to perform basic text
transformations on an input stream (a file or input from a
pipeline).</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed program</emphasis>: sed</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short description</title>

<para><command>sed</command> is used to filter and transform text files
in a single pass.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Sed Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &sed-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Sed depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils,
Diffutils, GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Texinfo.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-shadow" xreflabel="Shadow">
<title>Shadow</title>
<?dbhtml filename="shadow.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-shadow"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Shadow (4.0.3):
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.pld.org.pl/software/shadow/"/>

Shadow Newgrp Patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/shadow-4.0.3-newgrp-fix.patch"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Shadow</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &shadow-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Shadow package was created to strengthen the security
of system passwords.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: chage, chfn, chpasswd, chsh,
dpasswd, expiry, faillog, gpasswd, groupadd, groupdel, groupmod, groups, grpck,
grpconv, grpunconv, lastlog, login, logoutd, mkpasswd, newgrp, newusers,
passwd, pwck, pwconv, pwunconv, sg (link to newgrp), useradd, userdel, usermod,
vigr (link to vipw) and vipw</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>chage</command> is used to change the maximum number of
days between obligatory password changes.</para>

<para><command>chfn</command> is used to change a user's full name and
some other info.</para>

<para><command>chpasswd</command> is used to update the passwords of a
whole series of user accounts in one go.</para>

<para><command>chsh</command> is used to change a user's default
 login shell.</para>

<para><command>dpasswd</command> is used to change dial-up passwords for
user login shells.</para>

<para><command>expiry</command> checks and enforces the current password
expiration policy.</para>

<para><command>faillog</command> is used to examine the log of login
failures, to set a maximum number of failures before an account is blocked,
or to reset the failure count.</para>

<para><command>gpasswd</command> is used to add and delete members and
administrators to groups.</para>

<para><command>groupadd</command> creates a group with the given
name.</para>

<para><command>groupdel</command> deletes the group with the given
name.</para>

<para><command>groupmod</command> is used to modify the given group's
name or GID.</para>

<para><command>groups</command> reports the groups of which the given
users are members.</para>

<para><command>grpck</command> verifies the integrity of the group files,
<filename>/etc/group</filename> and <filename>/etc/gshadow</filename>.</para>

<para><command>grpconv</command> creates or updates the shadow group file
from the normal group file.</para>

<para><command>grpunconv</command> updates <filename>/etc/group</filename>
from <filename>/etc/gshadow</filename> and then deletes the latter.</para>

<para><command>lastlog</command> reports the most recent login of all
users, or of a given user.</para>

<para><command>login</command> is used by the system let users sign on.</para>

<para><command>logoutd</command> is a daemon used to enforce restrictions
on log-on time and ports.</para>

<para><command>mkpasswd</command> encrypts the given password using the
also given perturbation.</para>

<para><command>newgrp</command> is used to change the current GID during
a login session.</para>

<para><command>newusers</command> is used to create or update a whole
series of user accounts in one go.</para>

<para><command>passwd</command> is used to change the password for a user
or group account.</para>

<para><command>pwck</command> verifies the integrity of the password files,
<filename>/etc/passwd</filename> and <filename>/etc/shadow</filename>.</para>

<para><command>pwconv</command> creates or updates the shadow password file
from the normal password file.</para>

<para><command>pwunconv</command> updates <filename>/etc/passwd</filename>
from <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> and then deletes the latter.</para>

<para><command>sg</command> executes a given command while the user's GID
is set to that of the given group.</para>

<para><command>useradd</command> creates a new user with the given name,
or updates the default new-user information.</para>

<para><command>userdel</command> deletes the given user account.</para>

<para><command>usermod</command> is used to modify the given user's
login name, UID, shell, initial group, home directory, and the like.</para>

<para><command>vigr</command> can be used to edit the
<filename>/etc/group</filename> or <filename>/etc/gshadow</filename>
files.</para>

<para><command>vipw</command> can be used to edit the
<filename>/etc/passwd</filename> or <filename>/etc/shadow</filename>
files.</para>

<para><command>libmisc</command>...</para>

<para><command>libshadow</command> contains functions used by most
programs in this package.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Shadow Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &shadow-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Shadow depends on: Bash, Binutils, Bison, Coreutils,
Diffutils, GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-sysklogd" xreflabel="Sysklogd">
<title>Sysklogd</title>
<?dbhtml filename="sysklogd.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-sysklogd"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Sysklogd (1.4.1):
<ulink url="http://www.infodrom.org/projects/sysklogd/"/></literallayout>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Sysklogd</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &sysklogd-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Sysklogd package contains programs for recording
system log messages, such as those reported by the kernel.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: klogd and syslogd</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>klogd</command> is a system daemon for intercepting and
logging kernel messages.</para>

<para><command>syslogd</command> logs the messages that system programs
offer for logging. Every logged message contains at least a date stamp and a
hostname, and normally the program's name too, but that depends on how
trusting the logging daemon is told to be.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Sysklogd Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &sysklogd-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Sysklogd depends on: Binutils, Coreutils, GCC, Glibc, Make.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-sysvinit" xreflabel="Sysvinit">
<title>Sysvinit</title>
<?dbhtml filename="sysvinit.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-sysvinit"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Sysvinit (2.85):
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.cistron.nl/pub/people/miquels/sysvinit/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Sysvinit</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &sysvinit-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Sysvinit package contains programs to control the
startup, running and shutdown of all other programs.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: halt, init, killall5, last,
lastb (link to last), mesg, pidof (link to killall5), poweroff (link to halt),
reboot (link to halt), runlevel, shutdown, sulogin, telinit (link to init),
utmpdump and wall</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>halt</command> normally invokes shutdown with the -h flag,
except when already in runlevel 0, then it tells the kernel to halt the system.
But first it notes in the file <filename>/var/log/wtmp</filename> that the
system is being brought down.</para>

<para><command>init</command> is the mother of all processes. It reads its
commands from <filename>/etc/inittab</filename>, which normally tell it which
scripts to run for which runlevel, and how many gettys to spawn.</para>

<para><command>killall5</command> sends a signal to all processes, except
the processes in its own session -- so it won't kill the shell running the
script that called it.</para>

<para><command>last</command> shows which users last logged in (and out),
searching back through the file <filename>/var/log/wtmp</filename>. It can
also show system boots and shutdowns, and runlevel changes.</para>

<para><command>lastb</command> shows the failed login attempts, as logged
in <filename>/var/log/btmp</filename>.</para>

<para><command>mesg</command> controls whether other users can send
messages to the current user's terminal.</para>

<para><command>pidof</command> reports the PIDs of the given programs.</para>

<para><command>poweroff</command> tells the kernel to halt the system and
switch off the computer. But see halt.</para>

<para><command>reboot</command> tells the kernel to reboot the system.
But see halt.</para>

<para><command>runlevel</command> reports the previous and the current
runlevel, as noted in the last runlevel record  in
<filename>/var/run/utmp</filename>.</para>

<para><command>shutdown</command> brings the system down in a secure way,
signaling all processes and notifying all logged-in users.</para>

<para><command>sulogin</command> allows the superuser to log in. It is
normally invoked by init when the system goes into single user mode.</para>

<para><command>telinit</command> tells init which runlevel to enter.</para>

<para><command>utmpdump</command> displays the content of  the given login
file in a friendlier format.</para>

<para><command>wall</command> writes a message to all logged-in users.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Sysvinit Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &sysvinit-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Sysvinit depends on: Binutils, Coreutils, GCC, Glibc, Make.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-tar" xreflabel="Tar">
<title>Tar</title>
<?dbhtml filename="tar.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-tar"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Tar (1.13.25):
<ulink url="ftp://alpha.gnu.org/gnu/tar/"/></literallayout>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Tar</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &tar-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Tar is an archiving program designed to store and extract
files from an archive file known as a tar file.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: rmt and tar</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>rmt</command> is used to remotely manipulate a magnetic
tape drive, through an interprocess communication connection.</para>

<para><command>tar</command> is used to create and extract files from
archives, also known as tarballs.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Tar Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &tar-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Tar depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils,
Diffutils, GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-tcl" xreflabel="Tcl">
<title>Tcl</title>
<?dbhtml filename="tcl.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch05-tcl"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Tcl (8.4.5):
<ulink url="http://download.sourceforge.net/tcl/"/>
<ulink url="ftp://download.sourceforge.net/pub/sourceforge/tcl/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Tcl</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &tcl-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Tcl package contains the Tool Command Language.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: tclsh (link to tclsh8.4),
tclsh8.4</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed library</emphasis>: libtcl8.4.so</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short description</title>

<para><command>tclsh8.4</command> is the Tcl command shell.</para>

<para><command>libtcl8.4.so</command> is the Tcl library.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Tcl Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &tcl-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Tcl depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-texinfo" xreflabel="Texinfo">
<title>Texinfo</title>
<?dbhtml filename="texinfo.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-texinfo"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Texinfo (4.6):
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/texinfo/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Texinfo</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &texinfo-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Texinfo package contains programs used for reading,
writing and converting Info documents, which provide system
documentation.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: info, infokey, install-info,
makeinfo, texi2dvi and texindex</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>info</command> is used to read Info documents. Info
documents are a bit like man pages, but often go much deeper than just
explaining all the flags. Compare for example man tar and info tar.</para>

<para><command>infokey</command> compiles a source file containing Info
customizations into a binary format.</para>

<para><command>install-info</command> is used to install Info files. It
updates entries in the Info index file.</para>

<para><command>makeinfo</command> translates the given Texinfo source
documents into various other formats: Info files, plain text, or HTML.</para>

<para><command>texi2dvi</command> is used to format the given Texinfo
document into a device-independent file that can be printed.</para>

<para><command>texindex</command> is used to sort Texinfo index files.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Texinfo Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &texinfo-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Texinfo depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils,
Diffutils, GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Ncurses, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-utillinux" xreflabel="Util-linux">
<title>Util-linux</title>
<?dbhtml filename="util-linux.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-util-linux"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Util-linux (2.12):
<ulink url="http://ftp.cwi.nl/aeb/util-linux/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Util-linux</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &util-linux-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Util-linux package contains a number of miscellaneous
utility programs. Some of the more prominent utilities are used
to mount, unmount, format, partition and manage disk drives,
open tty ports and fetch kernel messages.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: agetty, arch, blockdev, cal,
cfdisk, chkdupexe, col, colcrt, colrm, column, ctrlaltdel, cytune, ddate,
dmesg, elvtune, fdformat, fdisk, fsck.cramfs, fsck.minix, getopt, hexdump,
hwclock, ipcrm, ipcs, isosize, line, logger, look, losetup, mcookie, mkfs,
mkfs.bfs, mkfs.cramfs, mkfs.minix, mkswap, more, mount, namei, parse.bash,
parse.tcsh, pg, pivot_root, ramsize (link to rdev), raw, rdev, readprofile,
rename, renice, rev, rootflags (link to rdev), script, setfdprm, setsid,
setterm, sfdisk, swapoff (link to swapon), swapon, test.bash, test.tcsh,
tunelp, ul, umount, vidmode (link to rdev), whereis and write</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>agetty</command> opens a tty port, prompts for a login name,
and then invokes the login program.</para>

<para><command>arch</command> reports the machine's architecture.</para>

<para><command>blockdev</command> allows you to call block device ioctls
from the command line.</para>

<para><command>cal</command> displays a simple calender.</para>

<para><command>cfdisk</command> is used to manipulate the partition table
of the given device.</para>

<para><command>chkdupexe</command> finds duplicate executables.</para>

<para><command>col</command> filters out reverse line feeds.</para>

<para><command>colcrt</command> is used to filter nroff output for terminals
that lack some capabilities such as overstriking and half-lines.</para>

<para><command>colrm</command> filters out the given columns.</para>

<para><command>column</command> formats a given file into multiple
columns.</para>

<para><command>ctrlaltdel</command> sets the function of the Ctrl+Alt+Del
 key combination, to a hard or a soft reset.</para>

<para><command>cytune</command> was used to tune the parameters of the
serial line drivers for Cyclades cards.</para>

<para><command>ddate</command> gives the Discordian date, or converts the
given Gregorian date to a Discordian one.</para>

<para><command>dmesg</command> dumps the kernel boot messages.</para>

<para><command>elvtune</command> can be used to tune the performance
and interactiveness of a block device.</para>

<para><command>fdformat</command> low-level formats a floppy disk.</para>

<para><command>fdisk</command> could be used to manipulate the partition
table of the given device.</para>

<para><command>fsck.cramfs</command> performs a consistency check on the
Cramfs filesystem on the given device.</para>

<para><command>fsck.minix</command> performs a consistency check on the
Minix filesystem on the given device.</para>

<para><command>getopt</command> parses options in the given command line.</para>

<para><command>hexdump</command> dumps the given file in hexadecimal, or
in another given format.</para>

<para><command>hwclock</command> is used to read or set the system's
hardware clock (also called the RTC or BIOS clock).</para>

<para><command>ipcrm</command> removes the given IPC resource.</para>

<para><command>ipcs</command> provides IPC status information.</para>

<para><command>isosize</command> reports the size of an iso9660
filesystem.</para>

<para><command>line</command> copies a single line.</para>

<para><command>logger</command> enters the given message into the system
log.</para>

<para><command>look</command> displays lines that begin with the given
string.</para>

<para><command>losetup</command> is used to set up and control loop devices.</para>

<para><command>mcookie</command> generates magic cookies, 128-bit random
hexadecimal numbers, for xauth.</para>

<para><command>mkfs</command> is used to build a filesystem on a device
(usually a harddisk partition).</para>

<para><command>mkfs.bfs</command> creates an SCO bfs filesystem.</para>

<para><command>mkfs.cramfs</command> creates a cramfs filesystem.</para>

<para><command>mkfs.minix</command> creates a Minix filesystem.</para>

<para><command>mkswap</command> initializes the given device or file to be
used as a swap area.</para>

<para><command>more</command> is a filter for paging through text one
screenful at a time. But less is much better.</para>

<para><command>mount</command> attaches the filesystem on the given device
to the given directory in the system's file tree.</para>

<para><command>namei</command> shows the symbolic links in the given
pathnames.</para>

<para><command>pg</command> displays a text file one screenful at a
time.</para>

<para><command>pivot_root</command> makes the given filesystem the new
root filesystem of the current process.</para>

<para><command>ramsize</command> could be used to set the size of the
RAM disk in a bootable image.</para>

<para><command>rdev</command> could be used to query and set the root
device and other things in a bootable image.</para>

<para><command>readprofile</command> reads kernel profiling information.</para>

<para><command>rename</command> renames the given files, replacing a given
string with another.</para>

<para><command>renice</command> is used to alter the priority of running
processes.</para>

<para><command>rev</command> reverses the lines of a given file.</para>

<para><command>rootflags</command> could be used to set the rootflags
in a bootable image.</para>

<para><command>script</command> makes a typescript of a terminal
session, of everything printed to the terminal.</para>

<para><command>setfdprm</command> sets user-provided floppy disk
parameters.</para>

<para><command>setsid</command> runs the given program in a new session.</para>

<para><command>setterm</command> is used to set terminal attributes.</para>

<para><command>sfdisk</command> is a disk partition table manipulator.</para>

<para><command>swapdev</command> could be used to set the swap device
in a bootable image.</para>

<para><command>swapoff</command> disables devices and files for paging
and swapping.</para>

<para><command>swapon</command> enables devices and files for paging
and swapping.</para>

<para><command>tunelp</command> is used to tune the parameters of the
line printer.</para>

<para><command>ul</command> is a filter for translating underscores into
escape sequences indicating underlining for the terminal in use.</para>

<para><command>umount</command> disconnects a filesystem from the
system's file tree.</para>

<para><command>vidmode</command> could be used to set the video mode
in a bootable image.</para>

<para><command>whereis</command> reports the location of binary, the
source, and the manual page for the given command.</para>

<para><command>write</command> sends a message to the given user. That is,
if that user has not disabled such messages.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Util-linux Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &util-linux-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Util-linux depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils,
Diffutils, GCC, Gettext, Glibc, Grep, Make, Ncurses, Sed, Zlib.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-vim" xreflabel="Vim">
<title>Vim</title>
<?dbhtml filename="vim.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-vim"/>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Vim (6.2):
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.vim.org/pub/editors/vim/unix/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Vim</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &vim-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Vim package contains a configurable text editor built to
enable efficient text editing.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: efm_filter.pl, efm_perl.pl, ex
(link to vim), less.sh, mve.awk, pltags.pl, ref, rview (link to vim), rvim
(link to vim), shtags.pl, tcltags, vi (link to vim), view (link to vim), vim,
vim132, vim2html.pl, vimdiff (link to vim), vimm, vimspell.sh, vimtutor
and xxd</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>efm_filter.pl</command> is a filter for creating an error
file that can be read by vim.</para>

<para><command>efm_perl.pl</command> reformats the error messages of the
Perl interpreter for use with the quickfix mode of vim.</para>

<para><command>ex</command> starts vim in ex mode.</para>

<para><command>less.sh</command> is a script that starts vim with less.vim.</para>

<para><command>mve.awk</command> processes vim errors.</para>

<para><command>pltags.pl</command> creates a tags file for perl code,
for use by vim.</para>

<para><command>ref</command> checks the spelling of arguments.</para>

<para><command>rview</command> is a restricted version of view: no shell
commands can be started and view can't be suspended.</para>

<para><command>rvim</command> is a restricted version of vim: no shell
commands can be started and vim can't be suspended.</para>

<para><command>shtags.pl</command> generates a tag file for perl scripts.</para>

<para><command>tcltags</command> generates a tag file for TCL code.</para>

<para><command>vi</command> starts vim in vi-compatible mode.</para>

<para><command>view</command> starts vim in read-only mode.</para>

<para><command>vim</command> is the editor.</para>

<para><command>vim132</command> starts vim with the terminal in
132-column mode.</para>

<para><command>vim2html.pl</command> converts vim documentation to
HTML.</para>

<para><command>vimdiff</command> edits two or three versions of a file with
vim and show differences.</para>

<para><command>vimm</command> enables the DEC locator input model on a
remote terminal.</para>

<para><command>vimspell.sh</command> is a script which spells a file and generates the syntax
statements necessary to highlight in vim.</para>

<para><command>vimtutor</command> teaches you the basic keys and commands
of vim.</para>

<para><command>xxd</command> makes a hexdump of the given file. It can
also do the reverse, so it can be used for binary patching.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Vim Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &vim-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Vim depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, Diffutils,
GCC, Glibc, Grep, Make, Ncurses, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>


<sect1 id="aa-zlib" xreflabel="Zlib">
<title>Zlib</title>
<?dbhtml filename="zlib.html"?>

<para>For installation instructions see <xref linkend="ch06-zlib"/>.</para>

<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Official Download Location</title>

<literallayout>Zlib (1.2.1):
<ulink url="http://www.gzip.org/zlib/"/></literallayout>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Contents of Zlib</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &zlib-contversion;.)</para> -->

<para>The Zlib package contains the libz library, which is used by some
programs for its compression and uncompression functions.</para>

<para><emphasis>Installed libraries</emphasis>: libz[a,so]</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short description</title>

<para><command>libz*</command> contains compression and uncompression
functions used by some programs.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title> </title><para> </para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Zlib Installation Dependencies</title>

<!-- <para>(Last checked against version &zlib-depversion;.)</para> -->

<para>Zlib depends on: Binutils, Coreutils, GCC, Glibc, Make, Sed.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>



</appendix>
