<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3CR3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % net-tools-entities SYSTEM "../ent/net-tools.ent">
  %net-tools-entities;
]>
<sect1 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" id="ch-system-net-tools" xreflabel="Net-tools">
<title>Installing Net-tools-&net-tools-version;</title>
<?dbhtml filename="net-tools.html"?>

<para>The Net-tools package contains programs for basic networking.</para>

<screen>Approximate build time:  0.1 SBU
Required disk space:     9.4 MB</screen>

<literallayout>Official download location for Net-tools (&net-tools-version;): 
<ulink url="http://www.tazenda.demon.co.uk/phil/net-tools/"/>
And for the patch:
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/patches/lfs/cvs/net-tools-&net-tools-version;-miitool-gcc33-1.patch"/></literallayout>

<para>For its installation Net-tools depends on: Bash, Binutils, Coreutils, GCC,
Glibc, Make.</para>



<sect2>
<title>Installation of Net-tools</title>

<para>If you don't know what to answer to all the questions asked during the
<command>make config</command> phase below, then just accept the defaults.
This will be just fine in the majority of cases. What you're asked here is a
bunch of questions about which network protocols you've enabled in your
kernel. The default answers will enable the tools from this package to work
with the most common protocols: TCP, PPP, and several others. You still need
to actually enable these protocols in the kernel -- what you do here is merely
telling the package to include support for those protocols in its programs,
but it's up to the kernel to make the protocols available.</para>

<para>First fix a small syntax problem in the sources of the
<command>mii-tool</command> program:</para>

<screen><userinput>patch -Np1 -i ../net-tools-&net-tools-version;-miitool-gcc33-1.patch</userinput></screen>

<para>Now prepare Net-tools for compilation (if you intend to accept the
defaults, you can skip all the questions by running <userinput>yes "" |
make config</userinput> instead):</para>

<screen><userinput>make config</userinput></screen>

<para>Compile the package:</para>

<screen><userinput>make</userinput></screen>

<para>And install it:</para>

<screen><userinput>make update</userinput></screen>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="contents-net"><title>Contents of Net-tools</title>

<para><emphasis>Installed programs</emphasis>: arp, dnsdomainname (link to
hostname), domainname (link to hostname), hostname, ifconfig, nameif, netstat,
nisdomainname (link to hostname), plipconfig, rarp, route, slattach and
ypdomainname (link to hostname)</para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>arp</command> is used to manipulate the kernel's ARP cache,
usually to add or delete an entry, or to dump the entire cache.</para>

<para><command>dnsdomainname</command> reports the system's DNS domain
name.</para>

<para><command>domainname</command> reports or sets the system's NIS/YP
domain name.</para>

<para><command>hostname</command> reports or sets the name of the current
host system.</para>

<para><command>ifconfig</command> is the main utility for configuring
network interfaces.</para>

<para><command>nameif</command> names network interfaces based on MAC
addresses.</para>

<para><command>netstat</command> is used to report network connections,
routing tables, and interface statistics..</para>

<para><command>nisdomainname</command> does the same as domainname.</para>

<para><command>plipconfig</command> is used to fine tune the PLIP device
parameters, to improve its performance.</para>

<para><command>rarp</command> is used to manipulate the kernel's RARP
table.</para>

<para><command>route</command> is used to manipulate the IP routing
table.</para>

<para><command>slattach</command> attaches a network interface to a serial
line. This allows you to use normal terminal lines for point-to-point links to
other computers.</para>

<para><command>ypdomainname</command> does the same as domainname.</para>

</sect2>



</sect1>
