<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="ch01-introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>

<para>LFS development takes place using three main systems. Firstly,
the mailing lists <userinput>lfs-book</userinput>,
<userinput>lfs-dev</userinput> and (to a lesser extent) 
<userinput>lfs-support</userinput>. Secondly the Bugzilla tracking
system, and thirdly the CVS server where the book itself is
stored. All of these services are provided by the server
<userinput>linuxfromscratch.org</userinput> also known as
<userinput>belgarath.linuxfromscratch.org</userinput> or more usually,
<userinput>belgarath</userinput>. This single server provides mailing
lists, web hosting, CVS hosting, ftp hosting, the Bugzilla system and
basically everything we use to work on the LFS project.</para>

<para>The actual LFS book itself is written using Docbook-XML and at
first can seem to be a daunting tangle of files. If you're confused, start
by looking at <filename>index.xml</filename>. At the bottom, you will
notice that it will reference the entity &amp;book;. Look up the entity
&amp;book; and you will see that it points to the file
<filename>book/book.xml</filename>. Continue in this way and you'll find
your way around the book soon enough.</para>

<para>The Bugzilla bug-tracking system for LFS can be found at <ulink url="http://bugs.linuxfromscratch.org"/>. In order to be able to
add, remove and edit bugs, you need to add an account and make sure you
are logged in whenever you wish to perform such an action.  You can
query and read the bug database without logging in or creating a user.
Note that all bugzilla messages are copied to the
<userinput>lfs-book</userinput> mailing list and that all editors
should be subscribed to this and the <userinput>lfs-dev</userinput>
list at a minimum.</para>

<para>Finally, there is the CVS server which will be discussed in the
following chapters.</para>

</sect1>
