<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="ch-cross-tools-introduction">
  <?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>

  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>This chapter shows you how to create cross platform tools.</para>

  <para>If for some reason you have to stop and come back later, remember
  to use the <command>su - lfs</command> command, and it will setup the
  build environment that you left.</para>

  <sect2>
    <title>Common Notes</title>

    <important>
      <para>Before issuing the build instructions for a package, the package
      should be unpacked as user <systemitem class="username">lfs</systemitem>,
      and a <command>cd</command> into the created directory should be
      performed. The build instructions assume that the <command>bash</command>
      shell is in use.</para>
    </important>

    <para>Several of the packages are patched before compilation, but only
    when the patch is needed to circumvent a problem. A patch is often needed
    in both this and the next chapters, but sometimes in only one or the other.
    Therefore, do not be concerned if instructions for a downloaded patch seem
    to be missing. Warning messages about <emphasis>offset</emphasis> or
    <emphasis>fuzz</emphasis> may also be encountered when applying a patch.
    Do not worry about these warnings, as the patch was still successfully
    applied.</para>

    <para>During the compilation of most packages, there will be several
    warnings that scroll by on the screen. These are normal and can safely
    be ignored. These warnings are as they appear&mdash;warnings about
    deprecated, but not invalid, use of the C or C++ syntax. C standards
    change fairly often, and some packages still use the older standard.
    This is not a problem, but does prompt the warning.</para>

    <important>
      <para>After installing each package, both in this and the next chapters,
      delete its source and build directories, unless specifically instructed
      otherwise. Deleting the sources saves space and prevents mis-configuration
      when the same package is reinstalled later.</para>
    </important>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
