<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/docbook-ng"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="ch-scatter-administrativa">
<title>Resources</title>
<?dbhtml filename="resources.html"?>


<section xml:id="ch-scatter-faq">
<title>FAQ</title>

<para>If during the building of your LFS system you encounter any errors, or
have any questions, or think you found a typo in the book, then please first
consult the FAQ (Frequently Asked Questions) at
<uri xlink:href="&faq-root;">&faq-root;</uri>.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="ch-scatter-irc">
<title>IRC</title>

<para>Several members of the LFS community offer assistance on our community
IRC (Internet Relay Chat) network. Before you utilize this mode of support, we
ask that you've at least checked the LFS FAQ (see above) and the mailing list
archives (see below) for the answer to your question. You can find the IRC
network at <uri>irc.linuxfromscratch.org</uri> or
<uri>irc.linux-phreak.net</uri> port 6667. The support channel is
named #LFS-support.</para>

</section>


<section xml:id="ch-scatter-maillists" xreflabel="Chapter 1 - Mailing lists">
<title>Mailing lists</title>

<para>The <uri>linuxfromscratch.org</uri> server is hosting a number
of mailing lists used for the development of the LFS project. These lists
include, among others, the main development and support lists.</para>

<para>For information on which lists are available, how to subscribe to them,
their archive locations, and so on, visit <uri xlink:href="&lfs-root;mail.html">&lfs-root;mail.html</uri>.</para>

</section>


<section xml:id="ch-scatter-newsserver">
<title>News server</title>

<para>All the mailing lists hosted at <uri>linuxfromscratch.org</uri>
are also accessible via the NNTP server. All messages posted to a mailing list
are copied to the corresponding newsgroup, and vice versa.</para>

<para>The news server can be reached at
<uri>news.linuxfromscratch.org</uri>.</para>

</section>


<section xml:id="ch-scatter-wiki">
<title>Wiki</title>

<para>For more information on a package, updated versions, tweaks, personal
experiences, and so on, see the LFS Wiki at <uri xlink:href="&wiki-root;">&wiki-root;</uri>. You can add information there yourself too, to help others.</para>

</section>


<section xml:id="ch-scatter-references">
<title>References</title>

<para>If you need still more detailed information on the packages,
you will find useful pointers on this page:
<uri xlink:href="http://www.109bean.org.uk/LFS-references.html">http://www.109bean.org.uk/LFS-references.html</uri>.</para>

</section>


<section xml:id="ch-scatter-mirrors" xreflabel="Chapter 1 - Mirror sites">
<title>Mirror sites</title>

<para>The LFS project has a number of mirrors set up world-wide to make
accessing the website and downloading the required packages more convenient.
Please visit the website at <uri xlink:href="&lfs-root;">&lfs-root;</uri> for a list of current mirrors.</para>

</section>


<section xml:id="ch-scatter-contactinfo">
<title>Contact information</title>

<para>Please direct all your questions and comments to one of the LFS mailing
lists (see above).</para>

</section>


</section>
